<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some treasure fetched out of rubbish: or, Three short but seasonable treatises (found in an heap of scattered papers), which Providence hath reserved for their service who desire to be instructed, from the Word of God, concerning the imposition and use of significant ceremonies in the worship of God. viz. I. A discourse upon 1 Cor. 14.40. Let all things be done decently and in order. Tending to search out the truth in this question, viz. Whether it be lawful for church-governours to command indifferent decent things in the administration of God's worship? II. An enquiry, whether the church may not, in the celebration of the Sacrament, use other rites significative than those expressed in the Scripture, or add to them of her own authority? III. Three arguments, syllogistically propounded and prosecuted against the surplice: the Cross in Baptism: and kneeling in the act of receiving the Lord's Supper.</title>
            <author>Cotton, John, 1584-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1046_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208022</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867028</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867028</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119318</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119318)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 155:E1046[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some treasure fetched out of rubbish: or, Three short but seasonable treatises (found in an heap of scattered papers), which Providence hath reserved for their service who desire to be instructed, from the Word of God, concerning the imposition and use of significant ceremonies in the worship of God. viz. I. A discourse upon 1 Cor. 14.40. Let all things be done decently and in order. Tending to search out the truth in this question, viz. Whether it be lawful for church-governours to command indifferent decent things in the administration of God's worship? II. An enquiry, whether the church may not, in the celebration of the Sacrament, use other rites significative than those expressed in the Scripture, or add to them of her own authority? III. Three arguments, syllogistically propounded and prosecuted against the surplice: the Cross in Baptism: and kneeling in the act of receiving the Lord's Supper.</title>
                  <author>Cotton, John, 1584-1652.</author>
                  <author>Nichols, Robert, Mr.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>John Cotton and Robert Nichols are identified within "To the Reader" as being the authors of the first 2 discourses and the third discourse, respectively.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oct: 8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rites and ceremonies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church --  Authority --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119318:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME TREASURE Fetched out of RUBBISH: OR, Three ſhort but ſeaſonable Treatiſes (found in an heap of ſcattered Papers), which Providence hath reſerved for their Service who deſire to be inſtructed, from the Word of God, concerning the Impoſition and Uſe of <hi>Significant Ceremonies</hi> in the Worſhip of God. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. A Diſcourſe upon 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in Order.</hi> Tending to ſearch out the Truth in this Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether it be lawful for <hi>Church-Governours</hi> to command indifferent decent things in the Adminiſtration of God's Worſhip?</item>
               <item>II. An Enquiry, Whether the Church may not, in the Celebration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, uſe other Rites ſignificative than thoſe expreſſed in the Scripture, or add to them of her own Authority?</item>
               <item>III. Three Arguments, Syllogiſtically propounded and proſecuted againſt the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice:</hi> The <hi>Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm: And <hi>Kneeling</hi> in the Act of receiving the Lord's Supper.</item>
            </list>
            <q>
               <p>Every Word of God is pure: Add not thou unto his Word, leſt he reprove thee, and thou be found a Liar,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 30.5, 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good: Abſtain from all appearance of evill,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Theſ. 5.21, 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind: For whatſoever is not of Faith is ſin,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 14.5, —23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119318:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119318:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THeſe enſuing Treatiſes were found laid by the Walls, and covered with duſt, in the ſtudy of an old <hi>Non-Conformiſt,</hi> (there being diverſe Copies of each, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeveral unknown hands:) And as Armour, Treaſure, and other things uſefull, hidden in the time of our late Wars, have ſince been brought forth for profitable Imployment; The like is hoped of theſe Papers (which have ſo long been kept in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs), if ſeriouſly peruſed by men of ſober minds. The fileings of Gold are precious: and the Charge of Chriſt is conſiderable, <hi>Joh. 6.12. Gather up the Fragments that are left, that nothing be loſt:</hi> Which Speech of his, may both warrant and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the collecting &amp; publiſhing of the precious divine Truths penned by Gods faithful Embaſſadours, for the edification of his Church.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>John Cotton<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that faithful Servant of Chriſt, (famous in both <hi>Englands</hi>) was the known Author of the firſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and (as its verily believed) of the ſecond alſo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Robert Nichols</hi> ſtudiouſly compoſed the third, who was a man, though leſs known, yet deſervedly famous for his great Abilities and profitable Miniſtry in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> for many years, where his memory is ſtill very precious.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119318:3"/>
When Reverend Dr. <hi>Morton</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> required in writing of thoſe Miniſters in his Dioceſs who did not conform to the Ceremonies, the Reaſons of this their refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal: Thereupon theſe three Arguments were by Mr. <hi>Nichols</hi> preſented unto him, atteſted by his own hand, and afterwards defended in diſpute with that learned Biſhop before many Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. The Biſhop being hereby convinced of the good mans Ability and Ingenuity, was his friend to his dying day.</p>
            <p>The publiſhing of theſe Papers is, for the preventing of the impoſition and practice of ſapleſs ſuperſtitions Ceremonies; which good end now deſigned may hopefully be effected, if the Lord will give men herein concerned to ſtudy theſe Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies with unbyaſſed hearts.</p>
            <p>It is notorious, that the preſſing of theſe <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, occaſioned woful Diviſions in the Church of Christ, with much affliction unto men, famous both for their parts and piety in their Generations, and men of truly tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and unblamable Converſation: And it is much to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, whether ever any reall ſpirituall advantage, come to Chriſtian Soul by the preſſing or by the obſerving of them.</p>
            <p>If the Lord would grant that Iſſue unto this Publication which is ſincerely intended and heartily prayed for, many thanks would be given unto his Majeſty, through Jeſus Chriſt, with comfort unto them that love Truth and Peace.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119318:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A DISCOURSE UPON 1 Cor. 14.40.</hi> Let all things be done decently and in Order.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Tending to ſearch out the Truth in this QUESTION,</hi> (viz.) Whether it be lawful for Church-<hi>Governors,</hi> to command indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent decent things in the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of <hi>God</hi>'s Worſhip.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL which that place holdeth forth touching this Point, may be ſummed up (for ought I can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern) in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the whole Church and every Member thereof, are to perform all the Duties of God's Worſhip in a decent and orderly manner.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What the Church and Members thereof are to do in this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119318:4"/>kind, that the Church-Governours may and ought to ſee it to be done.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It being the duty of Church-Governours to ſee that all things be done decently and orderly in the Congregation: It is therefore their part in eminent meaſure to be able to diſcern and judge what is decent and undecent, orderly or diſorderly.</p>
            <p>When I ſay it is their part, I mean, it is their duty; their Place and Authority requireth it: Not that they alwayes have a Power or Spirit of diſcerning, to judge aright in this caſe. For it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the High-Prieſts and Prophets, yea, and <hi>David</hi> himſelf, all of them thought it decent to bring back the Ark of God upon a new Cart; which afterwards <hi>David</hi> himſelf ſaw, and confeſſed it was not done after due order, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13.</p>
            <p>From whence it appeareth (ſince they alſo are ſubject to errours in this kind) that it will not be ſafe for them to judge and declare the decency of things, by no better Rule than their own Will and Pleaſure; but by ſuch Rules as the Holy Ghoſt directs us unto in this caſe, which are Scripture, Nature, Civil Cuſtom, (yea, and I willingly admit the lawful Cuſtom of the Church or Congregation, in which a man liveth, for to judge of decency;) by all theſe Rules, we have Warrant in Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14, 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.33.</p>
            <p>And indeed, they who are to approve themſelves, in all their proceedings (as <hi>Paul</hi> did, and all Church-Miniſters ought to do,) to every Man's Conſcience in the ſight of God; It is not for them to give the ground of their proceedings, only from their own Will and Pleaſure, but from ſuch Rules as every good Conſcience may ſee approvable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This place in hand holdeth forth alſo this further Truth, That what things the Church ſeeth (by the former Rules) to be indifferent and decent, or which Church-Governours ſhall declare ſo to be, thoſe things may lawfully be done.</p>
            <p>For the further clearing hereof, and the better diſcerning of the Power of Church-Governours in theſe matters: It may be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that of decent things lawful to be done in God's Church, ſome things are</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Indifferent and decent, As to preach in a Gown or Cloak, whereof the one is no more neceſſary or expedient than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
               <item>2. Expedient and decent; As to abide in ſingle life, or to enter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119318:4"/>into Marriage; of which, though Marriage in time of Perſecution be indifferent, yet ſingle life is much more expedient to prevent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Fleſh.</item>
               <item>3. Neceſſary and decent; either alwayes, as a Woman to keep ſilence in the Church, or at leaſt, <hi>Hic &amp; nunc,</hi> ſo as the neglect thereof would be uncomely to the light of Nature, Scripture, Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om: As a Woman to be veiled in the Congregation in the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Countries: So, to abſtain from Blood, whileſt the eating of it was offenſive to the Jew.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now, of ſuch things as are neceſſary and decent, Church-Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours have Power to give Order and Commandment, as did the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod</hi> at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> touching thoſe things they called neceſſary, (to wit, neceſſary during the time of the offence of the Jew, which was neceſſary to be avoided) <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28.</p>
            <p>Of ſuch things as are expedient and decent, the Church-Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours have Power to declare the decency and expediency of them; yea, and to adviſe and perſwade the practice thereof, but yet not to give an Order or Law to bind the People thereunto, further than themſelves ſhall find it decent and expedient for themſelves. Thus in Point of abiding in ſingle Life, in time of the Churches diſtreſs, the Apoſtle gave his Judgment and Advice 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.25, 40. and perſwaded to it, for avoiding trouble in the Fleſh, <hi>Ver.</hi> 26, 28. But would not bind them to it, neither in Point of Conſcience, nor of outward practice, as having no Commandment for it from the Lord, <hi>Ver.</hi> 25. In which reſpect, he calleth ſuch a Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if he had given it, <hi>a ſnare, Ver.</hi> 35. And herein the Power of Church-Governours falleth far ſhort of the Authority of Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, who may in civil matters make binding Laws for any thing expedient to publick weal, which Subjects are readily to ſubmit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> But it may be objected: <hi>Paul</hi> had Power to command <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> that which was convenient; therefore he might make a Law commanding the Church, expedient decent things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſw."/> It followeth not. For 1. It is one thing to give a Command for one thing, another to make a Law to bind him alwayes to do the like. 2. It's one thing to command a particular Perſon, who may owe himſelf to a Church-Governour (as <hi>Philemon</hi> did to <hi>Paul</hi>); another, to command, yea, to give a ſtanding Commandment, a bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Law to a whole Church, to whom he profeſſeth himſelf a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119318:5"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. over whom he hath no Authority, but ſtewardly, or oeconomical, to wit, when he ſpeaks in his Maſter's Name, not in his own. The Steward in a Family hath not power over his Maſter's Spouſe, but when he ſpeaks his Maſter's commands and directions, not his own. But of ſuch things as are onely indifferent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, I do not find in Scripture that ever Church-Governours did adviſe and perſwade them, much leſs charge and command them, leaſt of all make Laws to determine them. And that this place in hand (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.) doth not give them any ſuch Power (though it be much urged to this end), may appear from theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The place ſpeaks not of indifferent decent things, but of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary decent things, the neglect whereof was undecent by the light of Nature, and Scripture, and Cuſtom; As for men to pray with long haire, Women bare-headed; and for Women to ſpeak in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; and for many men to ſpeak at once.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The words of the place run not thus, Let all decent things be done; or, Let all things judged and declared by the Church to be decent, be done; but thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let all things</hi> (to wit, that are done in the Church, whether Prayer, or Propeſying, or other Ordinance of God,) <hi>be done decently;</hi> or in that decent manner which Church-Governours will appoint, or in ſome other: That the Apoſtle li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miteth not, but onely requireth, that all be done decently; which if it be ſo done, his Rule here preſcribed, is followed and fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſame may appear out of this place by this Argument: If this place of the Apoſtle did give Power and Authority to Church-Governours to command indifferent decent things, then he that ſhould tranſgreſs the Commandment of the Church, ſhould alſo tranſgreſs the Commandment of the Apoſtle: As, look what Order or Acts of Juſtice any Civil Governour doth by the Commiſſion of the King, he that violates ſuch Acts, or tranſgreſſeth ſuch Orders, tranſgreſſeth alſo againſt the Commiſſion of the King. But it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reth to be otherwiſe in this caſe; If the Church-Governours command a Miniſter to preach alwaies in a Gown (it being indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and decent ſo to do), he that ſhall now and then preach in a Cloak tranſgreſſeth the Command of the Church, but not of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. For he that preacheth in a Cloak preacheth alſo decently, which is all that the Rule of the Apoſtle requireth in this Point.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119318:5"/>
But becauſe this Point is of great Conſequence, both for Church-Governours and others to be truly informed in; give me leave to clear the ſame from ſome other Arguments. That it is not in the power of Church-Governours to command indifferent decent things by Order of Law.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That which exceedeth the bounds of Apoſtolical Authority, and ſtreightreth the bounds of Chriſtian Liberty, that is not in the Power of any Church-Governour.</p>
            <p>But to command indifferent decent things by Order of Law ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The former appeareth from the Apoſtle's Commiſſion granted to them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. where our Saviour giveth them Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>teach all Nations to obſerve all things whatſoever he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them.</hi> Now, all things whatſoever Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, are neceſſary, not indifferent, for the People to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p>If therefore the Apoſtles, over and above the Commandments of Chriſt (which are neceſſary), ſhould teach the People to obſerve in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things alſo which Chriſt hath not commanded, they ſhould exceed the bounds of their Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>It will be in vain to except: Our Saviour ſpeaketh here onely of matters of Doctrine and Faith, not Government and Order, unleſs it could be proved that our Saviour did elſe-where enlarge this Commiſſion, and gave them a more illimited Power in matters of Government and Order, or Indifferency; which (for ought I ſee) no man goeth about to do, unleſs it be from this place of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which hath already been cleared from ſuch meaning.</p>
            <p>As for the ſecond part of the Aſſumption, That to command in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different decent things ſtreightneth the bounds of Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is of it ſelf evident: For whereas (for example) a ſingle Man or Woman are at Liberty to marry where they will, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.39. If the Apoſtle had bound them from Marriage by any Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his, he had ſtreightned and deprived them of this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> It is wont to be objected againſt this, That Chriſtian Liberty ſtandeth not in the freedom of outward Actions, but in the freedom of Conſcience. As long therefore as there is no doctrinal neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty put upon the Conſcience to limit the uſe of outward things,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119318:6"/>Chriſtian Liberty is preſerved, though the uſe and practice of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things be limited.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſw."/> Whereto I anſwer, The Apoſtle in this caſe leaveth the People of God at liberty, not onely in point of Conſcience for lawfulneſſe to marry or not to marry, but even in outward action and practice; <hi>Let him do</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what he will, he ſinneth not, let them be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For a ſecond Reaſon it may be this; They who are not to judge or cenſure one another in differences about circumſtantial things, or matters of indifferency; they may not make a binding Law, that all men ſhall be of one mind, or of one practice in ſuch things: But the former is true, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Let not him that cateth, deſpiſe him that cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> If it be ſaid, The place onely ſpeaks of private Chriſtians, not of Church-Governours.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſw."/> The place ſpeaks of all Chriſtians, publick and private, ſeeing it reſerveth and referreth the Judgment of our Brethren, in ſuch things, not to publick Perſons, but onely to Chriſt: in the 4th, &amp; 10th. Verſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They who did accommodate themſelvs in the uſe of indifferent things, according to the judgment and practice of all Chriſtians, whereſoever they came; they did not make any Laws to bind Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to follow their Judgment and Practice in the uſe of things indifferent:</p>
            <p>But the Apoſtles of Chriſt did accommodate themſelves in the uſe of indifferent things according to the Judgment and Practice of the Chriſtians whereſover they came. As appeareth from the Apoſtle's Example, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20, 21, 22. <hi>To the Jews I became as a Jew,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> But it may be ſaid, Though the Apoſtles choſe rather to uſe their Liberty than their Authority, in theſe things indifferent, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they came; yet, if they had pleaſed, they might have uſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Authority, binding all Chriſtians to their Judgment and Practice in ſuch things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſw."/> 1. Doubtleſs, if they had received any ſuch Authority, they would in ſome place, at ſome time or other, have claimed it, and practiſed it. A Sword never uſed, ruſteth in the Scabbard: And <hi>fruſtra eſt potentia quae nunquam venit in actum,</hi> is a true Axiome, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſpeak of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119318:6"/>
2. The Apoſtle himſelf cleareth this Point, when he confeſſeth, he did thus accommodate himſelf even to the weakneſs of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, leſt he ſhould abuſe his Authority in the Goſpel, <hi>Ver.</hi> 18, 19, 20. Oh that ſuch Church-Gouernours, as plead their ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles, and do challenge in ſundry paſſage; of Government Apoſtolical Authority, would alſo be pleaſed to ſtudy and emulate an Apoſtolical Spirit.</p>
            <p>For a fourth Argument, let it be this: If the Apoſtles, and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and Brethren at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did reach their Authority no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than to lay upon the Diſciples necks the yoak and burthen of neceſſary things (and that onely during the time while they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neceſſary); then may not any ſucceeding Synod reach their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to lay upon the Church Commandments and Canons of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things: For the Synod at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was the pattern and precedent of all ſucceeding Synods; For <hi>primum in uno<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> genere eſt menſura reliquorum.</hi> And our Saviour teacheth us to confute Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations from Primitive Patterns, with this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Nou ſic fuit ab initio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Synod at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> reached their Authority no further than to lay a Commandment upon the Diſciples onely touching <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things,</hi> Act. 15.28. Neceſſary I ſay, either in themſelves, as abſtaining from Fornication; or at leaſt in reſpect of preſent offence, as Abſtinence from blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Let me conclude with this Argument, taken from the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> his enter-courſe with the Apoſtle <hi>Peter.</hi> If the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> was to be blamed for compelling the Gentiles by his example to obſerve the indifferent Ceremonies of the Jews; then other Church-Governours will be to blame, for compelling Chriſtians by Law, and by grievous Cenſures to obſerve the Ceremonies in Queſtion, though they were indifferent:</p>
            <p>But the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> telleth us, <hi>Peter</hi> was to be blamed in this caſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11, 14.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe, No man will here except, as is wont to be excepted, againſt ſuch Arguments as plead for the refuſing of our Ceremonies, upon ſuch grounds as <hi>Paul</hi> urged againſt yielding to the Jewiſh Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, as they were urged by the falſe Apoſtles, <hi>(viz.)</hi> with O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of neceſſity unto Salvation. For <hi>Peter</hi>'s yielding at that time to the Jewiſh Ceremonies, was not out of opinion of their neceſſity to Salvation, but only out of fear of offence, and care to prevent it, <hi>Ver.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119318:7"/>
The Sum of all this, will lead us by the hand one ſtep further: If it be a ſin in Church-Governours to command, eſpecially upon ſo ſtrict panalt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, indifferent decent things; it ſhall be a ſin alſo in Miniſters and other private Chriſtians to ſubſcribe <hi>ex animo,</hi> and to yield Obedience to ſuch Command; although the Ceremonies commanded were indeed as good as they be pretended, (which, I believe, are not indifferent decent things.) For, doth not ſuch vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Subſcription and Conformity to them build up our Church-Governours; yea, and with them the Soveraign Civil Magiſtrate alſo in this confidence, that ſuch Commandments are as well law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully given by them, as received and obeyed by us? Now, to build up or edify a Brother unto ſin, is no better than to offend a Brother: For the proper definition of an Offence, is, That which <hi>edifies a Brother unto ſin,</hi> as the original word expreſſeth it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.10. And ſo to ſin againſt my Brother, is to wound his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; yea, (and as much as in me lyeth) to cauſe him to periſh for whom Chriſt dyed, which is no better than ſpiritual Murther, even the Murther of his Soul.</p>
            <p>Now, if thus to edify my Brother unto ſin, be ſo hainous an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; how much more hainous an Offence is it, to edify our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours to the giving and urging of ſuch Commandments; yea, to the ſharp cenſuring of all others; as refractory and factious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who chooſe rather to undergo the loſs of the greateſt-Comforts they enjoy in this World, than to wound the Conſciences either of themſelves or their Governours.</p>
            <p>It is true, by forbearing Obedience to theſe Commandments we offend the Spirits of our Governours, and make them to be (though cauſleſly) offended with us; but by yielding Obedience to theſe things, we ſhould offend their Conſciences in edifying them unto Sin, and provoke the Lord to be offended with them and us. It is not for Chriſtians, much leſs for Miniſters, to redeem our peace and liberty at ſo dear a price, as the hazard of the blood of ſo many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soul, eſpecially of our Governours in higheſt place.</p>
            <p>Now, I ſhall proceed to anſwer another great Queſtion for clearing the Point in hand.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="inquiry">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119318:7"/>
            <head>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Queſt."/> May not the Church, in the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Sacraments, uſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rites ſignificative than thoſe expreſſed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or add to them of her own Authority?</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſw."/> No, but ſhe is to reſt in the uſe of thoſe Seals God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: For all ſigns of mens deviſing cannot teach or ſtir up true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, but delude, and nouriſh Superſtition. Beſides, to do any thing which doth derogate from the Seal of Kings, and their Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative therein, we know how dangerous it is in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; ſo certainly, to joyn Seals with God's Seals in his Church, is a Point will hardly be anſwered. It beſeemeth us to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge God ſo wiſe, in the Signs that he hath choſen, as to hold it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption for any to imitate him in deviſing of the like: For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, none might deviſe an Oyl like his, nor an Altar beſides his;<note place="margin">Exod. 30 38. Lev. 17.3. Lev. 10.1.</note> none a fire like the fire that he hath choſen; yea, in his works them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, he is not magnified as he deſerveth, till we confeſs, None is able to come after him; and till we ſay, <hi>Who is able to do the like?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain where man deviſeth new ſigns, the ſigns of God are vilified, as if they were from an Humane Spirit; yea, as if they were leſſe fit and convenient: And whereas Man is carnall, blind, and impotent, and yet a lover of his own devices (no leſſe than <hi>Pigmalion</hi> of his own Picture); if he ſhould be ſuffered to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent new Signs, they would be carnal and not ſpiritual; dead, having no Power; dark, veiling the brightneſs of the Sacraments: and yet more loved and delighted in, than the Sacraments themſelves.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calr.</hi> opuſc. de Neceſ. R form. <hi>pag. 59. Joſeph.</hi> Antiq. lib. <hi>15.</hi> cap. <hi>8. Aegeſip.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> For example, a Temple built on <hi>Garezim</hi> (like the Temple of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>) overtopped the Temple; And to what fame aroſe a Temple which <hi>Orias</hi> built in <hi>Heliopolis,</hi> like to that of the Lord's in <hi>Jury?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What our heavenly King delivereth his People muſt be marked with no other form or print ſave that which is framed in his Word, and in his own Sacraments: And however God permitted the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119318:8"/>Fathers to fail in heart in ſome particulars, againſt thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Doctrine; yet they ever diſallowed and abhorred the chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſigns inſtituted by God, and the deviſing of others determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſignify the ſame thing, that was ſealed by the Sacraments. The memory of the <hi>Barſamani</hi> and <hi>Semidalitae</hi> is abhorred,<note place="margin">Daneſ. <hi>in Aug. de haer.</hi> cap. 64. Concil. Braca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſ. 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan. 6. <hi>in Trullo</hi> cap. 99. Aug. <hi>de haereſ.</hi> cap. 28. Can. <hi>Apeſt.</hi> c. 3. Decret. <hi>par.</hi> 3. <hi>diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.2.3.4.5.6.7. Concil. Conſt. 6. <hi>in Trullo.</hi> cap. 32. Lamb. Dan. <hi>in</hi> Aug <hi>de haer.</hi> cap. 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 64. Concil. <hi>Antiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorenſ.</hi> can. 8.</note> for that inſtead of Bread they uſed Meal, even as others are utterly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for bringing in Orapes inſtead of Wine: The <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mans</hi> added ſodd meat to the Bread and Wine of the Lord's Supper: The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarli</hi> changed Wine into Water: The <hi>Artotyritae</hi> added Cheeſe to the Bread in the Supper, upon an imitation of ancient times, when the fruits of the Earth, and the fruits of the Cattel were wont to be offered to the Lord: Others added Hony to the Wine in the Supper, and ſome Milk: But all theſe are condemned, becauſe they are not in the Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Theſe Hereticks and Sects condemned, brought in their deviſed ſigns as parts of the Sacraments, which is a thing to be condemned: But what ſay you of ſigns deviſed by humane Authority, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Sacraments, not as parts, but for ſignification only?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Signs annexed to the Sacraments for ſignification, to declare or teach what God promiſeth to man, or what duty man oweth to God, are parts of the Sacraments, no more than ſome of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and the Reaſons brought to condemn them, do caſhiere and caſt out theſe alſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For if he be not devout but preſumptuous who adminiſtreth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than he hath <hi>received of the Lord,</hi> then muſt all ſtrange ſigns be abandoned which hath not been ſeen and approved of God: The charge of the Lord to his People is this, <hi>Ye ſhall do my Judgments and keep my Ordinances to walk therein;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 18 4. Deut. 27.26. Gal. 3.10. Deut. 6.13. Mat. 4 10. Deut. 12.32. Deut. 4 1.2. Zanch. <hi>d. Scrip.</hi> q. 8. <hi>prop.</hi> 1. <hi>Co. ſ.</hi> 2 <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g.</hi> Exod. 12.24.43. &amp; 27.21. &amp; 29.9. &amp; 30.21. Deut. 4.1.</note> the meaning is plainly this, Ye ſhall obſerve all mine Ordinances, Moral and Ceremonial, and them onely; as the words of this Law is explained by the Apoſtle. <hi>All things which are written in the Book of this Law.</hi> And <hi>him thou ſhalt ſerve,</hi> is expounded by our Saviour, <hi>Him onely thou ſhalt ſerve;</hi> more expreſly the ſame Commandment is repeated in other places: <hi>What things ſoever I command you obſerve to do it, thou ſhalt not add unto it, nor diminiſh from it;</hi> To what might they not add? neither to the Law Moral nor Ceremonial, as the Word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, and all Circumſtances of the Text do convince: For in the former of thoſe places, <hi>Iſrael</hi> is exhorted to hearken unto the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and Ordinances of the Lord; under which two words (often
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119318:8"/>joyned together) are compriſed all duties of the Law moral and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial: And thereupon immediately follow theſe words,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.8.40. Deut. 5.1. and 6.1. and 12.1. Mal. 4.4. Lev. 18.5. and 19.37. and 26.22.18.22. Deut. 4.1, 2. Exod. 25.9, 40. and 27.19.</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall not add unto the Word (or things) which I commanded unto you.</hi> The ſame is more clear in the ſecond place: for having recited many Precepts Ceremonial, and ſome few Moral; he concludeth, Whatſoever I command you to obſerve, take heed to obſerve it, &amp;c. And <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf faithfully in this performed the charge of God; for having received a Commandment from him to make all things pertaining to the Tabernacle, according to the pattern ſhewed in the Mount, he preſumed not to add one pin to that was ſhewed him, but ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed his Sampler in every point.<note place="margin">Exod. 39.42, 43.</note> And if <hi>Moſes</hi> durſt not challenge authority of himſelf to ordain Sacramentall Rite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex them to the holy Ordinances of the Lord, how ſhall we be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the Church hath any liberty herein? what reaſon can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven why that ſhould be warrantable in this age of the Church, and in that unlawfull? If the Church will preſume to claim any ſuch Prerogative, it is neceſſary ſhe produce the Charter wherein the Lord hath confirmed ſuch a Priviledg unto her, which before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to that his Faithfull ſervant, with whom he was pleaſed to ſpeak familiarly, and in moſt friendly manner. The worthy Reformers of Religion, who lived in the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> after the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> knew no ſuch grant, for they kept themſelves preciſely to the Law of the Lord by the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> not turning there-from in any thing, without ſpecial and extraordinary inſpiration. <hi>David</hi> gave to <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſon,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 28.12.19.</note> the pattern of all that he had by the Spirit, of the Courts of the houſe of the Lord, of all the Chambers round about, &amp;c. And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſet the Levites in the houſe of the Lord,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 29.25.</note> with Cymballs, with Pſalteries, and with Harps, according to the commandment of <hi>David,</hi> and of <hi>Gad</hi> the Kings Seer, and <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prothet, for ſo was the Commandment of the Lord by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. Ask the Scripture whether ever the godly Kings among the <hi>Jews</hi> had any ſuch Authority to bring in any ſpecial Action or Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony into the ſervice of God without ſpecial warrant; Search the Scriptures about this matter, and if they anſwer <hi>[Nay]</hi> to this demand, let us take heed to our ſelves, that we preſume not beyond commiſſion. Cut off thoſe places before cited; the Papiſts grant, the perfection of the Word of God may well be concluded: Our Writers do ſubſtantially prove the ſufficiency of the Scripture in matter neceſſary to Salvation, becauſe we are forbidden to add ought
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119318:9"/>to the Word written (for of that the Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is meant), or to take ought from it; and by the ſame reaſon, the ſufficiency of the Scriptures in matters Ceremonial, is eſtabliſhed; for thſe places muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Ceremonies no leſs then other things.<note place="margin">Deſcrip. q. 8. prop. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Zanchius</hi> thus urgeth this argument; And leſt any Papiſt (ſaith he) ſhould except and ſay, Neither do we think it lawfull to add to thoſe things which pertain to Internall, and ſo to Spirituall piety and worſhip of God; but onely the Controverſy is of external Ceremonies; I pray you, conſider of what things the Lord ſpeaketh in that Chapter, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. Of what Ceremonies, ſacred Rites, and Judicial Laws; for in the Hebrew, it ſaith thus, <hi>Hear now, O Iſrael, the Statutes, and the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> That word <hi>Hachukim</hi> doth properly ſignify Ceremonious Rites of worſhip: Therefore the Lord would teach, that nothing is to be added, not onely to the Moral Precepts, and internal wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but alſo to the Ceremonial-Rites and Inſtitutions; which may be further confirmed againſt our Adverſaries, by the Authority of the vulgar Tranſlation, Interpreting it in <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.5. Ceremonies; And the Opinion of <hi>Stapleton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Relect. prin. fid. doct. cont. 4. q. 3. art. 3. arg. 10. Anſw. to the Adm. pag. 30.</note> who making anſwer to that place alledged by our Divine, to confirm the perfection of Scripture againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written traditions; ſaith, It is eſpecially to be underſtood of the Ceremonies. This is acknowledged by <hi>D. Whiteg.</hi> God (ſaith he) in the old Law to his people, preſcribed perfect and abſolute Laws, not onely Moral and Judicial, but Ceremonial alſo; neither was there the leaſt thing to be done in the Church omitted in the Law; And therefore for them at that time, and during that State, it was not lawfull to add any thing, nor take any thing away, no not in Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and civill Laws.<note place="margin">Bill. de Pont. Rom. l. 4. c. 17.</note> The Jews (ſaith another) had a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of particular Rites, moſt fitly agreeing to the Polity of their Church and Common-wealth. But what? hath God left no greater liberty to the Church in the time of the Goſpel, to ordain ſignificant Ceremonies; than was before given unto the Synagogue of the <hi>Jews?</hi> No ſurely, both the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Church are tyed to the direction of the Scriptures, without which they might not preſume to do any thing in theſe matters: How can theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be alledged with truth of reaſon againſt our Adverſaries, to prove the perfection of Scripture in oppoſition to unwritten Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. If the Church have authority now to ordain Ceremonies without direction of the Word, which then ſhe had not: eaſily might they reply, That that Injunction did not concern us at this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119318:9"/>day, ſeeing more liberty is given to us touching the Inſtitution of external Rites pertaining to the worſhip of God, then was granted to the <hi>Jews.</hi> And if we may add without warrant of the Word, what, and where they might not: Surely the Scripture was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rule to them: In another manner than it is to us. <hi>Zanchius</hi> therefore objecting in the name of the Papiſts, That if theſe places muſt be underſtood of the Ceremonial Law, then it pertaineth not to us, inaſmuch as the Ceremonial Laws are now changed: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth anſwer, That that Precept doth pertain to us, which is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt (ſaith he) if you conſider the end of the Commandment; What end? That we ſhould obey thoſe things, and thoſe things onely that God hath commanded, adding nothing, detracting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Therefore when the ſame God hath by his Son given Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts concerning Ceremonies of the New Teſtament, and willeth us ſimply to obey them; the force of that Precept remains, Thou ſhalt <hi>add nothing, diminiſh nothing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 28.19, 20.</note> Moreover Chriſt himſelf plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commandeth the ſame, <hi>Baptize them into the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, teaching them to obſerve whatſoever I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</hi> What is this, but ye ſhall not add or diminiſh. Again, what is that that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>I have received of the Lord, what I have delivered unto you:</hi> but that it is not lawfull to add nor dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh? Then he concludes, Therefore the force of the Precept in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch. de ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo praec. tit. de ext. cult. q. 1. Tam igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur nobis non licet addere his vel detrahere quam eriam non licebat Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeis addere vel detrahere de illis.</note> of not adding or diminiſhing any thing in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of God, doth remain perpetual, even concerning Ceremonies, and holy Rites, and pertains to us. The <hi>Jews</hi> had liberty in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain matters of order pertaining to the ſervice of God, as we now have. In matter of Ceremonies we are tyed to the Word of God, as they were. We have no Ceremonies but two, the Ceremonies or Sacraments of Baptiſm, and the Lords Supper; and we have as certain direction to celebrate them, as they had to celebrate their Ceremonies; and fewer and leſs difficulties can ariſe of ours, than of theirs; we have no ſpecial hour, place, or manner of celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſſigned for them; the like may be ſaid of many Jewiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, What hour had they for their ordinary and daily Sacrifices?<note place="margin">Jun. et Trem. in act. 13.15.</note> was not it left to the order of the Church what places were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their ſeveral dwellings to hear the Word of God Preached continually, when they came not to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> The Word was commanded to be Preached, but no mention made in what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar method, what manner of place, Pulpit, Seat, or Chair they ſhould
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119318:10"/>have, and yet they had theſe: they had alſo forms of Burial and Marriage, though nothing be commanded concerning them: The liberty of the Chriſtian Church ſtandeth in freedome from the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of Jewiſh Ceremonies,<note place="margin">Beza annot. in act. 6.</note> not in power to ordain new Rites at her pleaſure, when thoſe which God himſelf inſtituted are aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for then ſhould our condition in the time of the Goſpell be far worſe in many reſpects then theirs was in the time of the Law: for whereas it is the vertue of a good Law,<note place="margin">Ariſt. ad The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. Ra. 1.3.</note> to leave as little undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and without the compaſs of the Law, as may be. If we have no Word for divers things, wherein the <hi>Jews</hi> had particular direction; there was greater perfection in the Law given unto them, then in the Word which is left to the Chriſtian Church. Again,<note place="margin">Calv. opuſ. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſ. verſipel. pag. 413.</note> the Ordinances of God, which are ever behovefull, are not ſo burthenſome, as are the unprofitable inventions of men; it is far better to bear the yoak of God, then to be in ſubjection unto the meer pleaſure of ſinfull men. And then, If the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> was to admit of no Ceremonies, but what was preſcribed unto her of the Lord; whereas the Chriſtian Church is to ſtand to the Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement of her Guides and Governours: the Bondage and Infancy of the Jewiſh,<note place="margin">Bel. de effect. Sac. l. 2. c. 32. Bell. de Mon. l. 2. c. 13. arg. 9. reſp. &amp; pont. r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. lib. 4. cap. 17. Chryſoſt. hom. 52. in Matth. cited by D. Whitak. de ſc. q. 9. c. 14.</note> is much to be preferred before the liberty and ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Chriſtian Church. It is replied, that the adding and diminiſhing ſpoken of, doth not mean addition of preſervation, but addition of corruption; like as the fraudulent Coyner of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney doth not corrupt the Kings Coyn, either by adding baſer metral unto it, or by clipping any ſilver from it, and in both kinds he is a Traytor. How little doth this differ from the Jeſuites gloſs upon this Text: God commands (ſaith he) nothing to be added to his Precept to corrupt it, but not ſome things which may perfect it. Can humane deviſed Rites preſerve the Ordinances of God from corruptions; or rather are not all ſuch additions manifeſt corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? When God hath given to <hi>Moſes</hi> particular determinations of all ſymbolical Rites pertaining to his worſhip, had it not been an addition of corruption in him, if upon his own head he had annexed any deviſed ſignificative Rites unto them. <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> himſelf grants, it had been; when in his third anſwer, he labours (but to ſmall purpoſe) to put this difference betwixt the ſtate of the old and New Teſtament;<note n="†" place="margin">Petitur prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium, quia et hoc ipſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria eſt quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet nova lex quod divina additur; quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dequidem iſte ſibi addi vetat. Tilen. de pot. l. 4. c. 17. not. 11. viſe Lubbert. de Pap. Rom. l. 8. cap. 10.</note> That in the one, all Rites pertaining to the worſhip of God, were particularly determined, but not in the other. And when the Jeſuite confeſſeth in his firſt anſwer to that Argument ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119318:10"/>by our Divines, againſt humane Laws binding Conſcience;<note place="margin">Jun. ani. in <hi>Bel. de Pont.</hi> Rom. lib. 4. cap. 17.</note> that it is unlawful to add to the things commanded; As, to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice two Lambs, when God hath commanded onely one; doth he not grant by neceſſary Conſequence, that when God hath appointed that Baptiſm ſhould be adminiſtred with Water, it is unlawfull to add thereto Oyl, Cream, Salt, Spittle, and ſuch like? Moreover, to give Man Authority to add Rites of Information to the holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God; what is it but to prefer the folly of Man before the Wiſdom of God, as though his ſacred Inſtitutions muſt borrow reverence or defence from humane Forgeries:</p>
            <p>Doth not this Diſtinction open a wide gapp to let in manifold Abuſes into God's Worſhip, under the colour of Addition of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation? Doth it not much impaire the perfection of Scripture, when Rites Sacramental, tending to preſerve the purity and due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Chriſt's Inſtitutions, ſhall be eſteemed lawful in the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Worſhip of God, when they find no footing to ſtand on in the Word of God:<note place="margin">D. <hi>Lambard.</hi> l. 4. diſt. 3. c. 1. D. Sp. pag. 32. D. <hi>Cov.</hi> againſt <hi>Per.</hi> pag. 123. D. <hi>Whitg.</hi> Anſ. Adm. pag. 32. Preſerve, or keep carefully that which is committed to our truſt. 1 Tim. 6.20. <hi>Cajet.</hi> interprets this place thus; <hi>Inhibetur addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, etiam pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textu Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dien di man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data Dei.</hi> See. <hi>Calv.</hi> in Mat. 15.</note> The Synagogue of <hi>Rome</hi> doth not maintain her Addition to be of abſolute neceſſity, or eſſential parts of the Sacraments, but inſtituted of the Church for ſignification and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; and yet they are juſtly cenſured as unlawful, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Authority of the Holy Scripture. The Lord chargeth that we do not add, that ſo we may preſerve it.</p>
            <p>This Argument might here be ſhut up, but that to prevent ſome Objections, it is good to enquire what is an Addition to the Word. The Patrons of ſignificant Ceremonies ſay, An unlawful Addition to any of Chriſt's Sacraments is onely that which either participates therewith in all or at leaſt in the chief and proper ends thereof, or is added for Complement thereof, as neceſſary, and ſo, unchangeable. To add to the Word, is to ordain ſomewhat as a thing abſolutely neceſſary, and pertaining to the Eſſence of Worſhip: Thoſe add to the Word,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Who teach or decree any thing, either in matters of Faith or Ceremonies, contrary to the Word.</item>
               <item>2. Thoſe that make any thing neceſſary to Salvation not contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Word.</item>
               <item>3. Such as put any Religion or Opinion of merit in any thing that they themſelves have invented, beſides the Word of God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Laſt of all, They add to the Word, which forbid that thing for a thing of it ſelf unlawful, which God doth not forbid; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119318:11"/>make that ſin which God doth not make ſin.</p>
            <p>But in all theſe definitions, that is left out which <hi>Moſes</hi> meant ſpecially to comprehend, which is, not to do more nor to do leſſe than he had commanded: Every unlawful Tradition is contrary to the Word, which forbiddeth all ſuch Additions. But as the Word contrary in ſtrict ſenſe, is oppoſite to that which is beſides the Word, it reacheth not (with the other particulars added to it,) to expreſs what is an Addition prohibited. The Lord Jeſus is the ſole Doctor of his Church, whoſe Office it is to teach by word and ſign, and therefore whatſoever is deviſed by Man to inſtruct by outward reſemblance, and to admoniſh by ſtriking the ſenſes by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation; that is an unwarrantable Addition. God is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sealer of his Promiſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tho: Aquin. pag. 3. q. 60.</hi> Cajetan. <hi>ibid.</hi> Cerimonalis lex perfecta in Sc. traditur in libris <hi>Moſis,</hi> ubi nulla Ceremonia ne minutiſſima quidem praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa eſt. <hi>Wh. de Sc. q. 6. cap. 14.</hi> Quod uni Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum populo per <hi>Moſen</hi> dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genterſatis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripta eſſent, <hi>&amp;c. Janſen. cond. cap. 120.</hi>
               </note> and Signifier of his Will, by things ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Sacrament, and by words ſimilitudinary in the Scripture; to him it appertaineth to determine what ſigns muſt be uſed to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy. In the time of the Law, when ſigns reigned, none were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful but ſuch as were ſhewed in the pattern upon the Mount; much more in the time of the Goſpel, when ſhadows are aboliſhed, what God hath not inſtituted is to be abandoned; <hi>Moſes</hi> durſt not add of his own head to thoſe ſigns that were appointed of the Lord, though to ends inferiour; as profitable onely to ſignify, not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite; as matters of expediency to explain and declare what was repreſented, not of abſolute neceſſity: And what had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in him, is intolerable in us, being delivered from the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogy of the Law: In thoſe things God hath preciſely determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; in thoſe actions, the whole form whereof God hath of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſet down to be obſerved, we may not otherwiſe do than exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he hath commanded. Herein, what is not expreſſed, or by good conſequence enjoyned, is to be held unwarrantable: In this caſe, the deviſing of new Rites to ſignify the truths taught in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or ſealed in the Sacraments, cannot be deemed leſs than an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Addition;<note place="margin">Babing. in com. 2. pag. 95.</note> upon this ground our Divines have caſt Images out of the Church, not onely for teaching ill, but for teaching at all; becauſe God alloweth no Teacher but himſelf, nor means of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but his holy Word and Sacraments. And when the Son of God hath inſtituted the Sacraments, and he hath commanded them to be adminiſtred in certain Rites, inſtituted of himſelf; It is a very hard Queſtion (ſaith <hi>Chenmitius</hi>) whether Man be permitted to add others over and above,<note place="margin">Exam. Conc. Trid. part. 2. tit. de. rit. Bapt.</note> under any pretence Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> reaſoneth thus
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119318:11"/>againſt the Rites of Popiſh Confirmation:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Willets</hi> Cont. 14. q. 1. par. 5. pag. 719. Col. 2.17.</note> All of them are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, having myſtical and typical ſignifications and ſhadows, which agree not with the Nature of the Goſpel; for all ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows are now paſt, the Body being come: It is contrary to the Rule of the Goſpel there ſhould be ſuch Types, Shadows, and Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications brought into the Service of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Id.</hi> Cont. 12. q. 8. Arg. 1. pag. 504.</note> Therefore we dare not allow of theſe deſcriptions of unlawful Additions before-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not onely becauſe they cannot be juſtified by Scripture, as all good Expoſitions Theological muſt and ought; but alſo the whole current of Scripture plainly ſheweth it to be too ſtrict, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in part by that which hath been already ſaid, and remaineth to be proved more at large hereafter: <hi>Unde jus prodit, interpretatio quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> procedat. Decret.</hi> Grego. <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 39. <hi>cap.</hi> 31. <hi>Innocent.</hi> 3. <hi>Quis legum Aenigmata ſolvere idoneus eſſe videtur, niſi is cui ſoli Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlatorem eſſe conceſſum eſt.</hi> Cod. lib. 1. Tit. 14. leg. 9. &amp; 10.11. &amp; Tit. 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As in matters of Faith, ſo in matters of Ceremonies ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative pertaining to the Worſhip of God, an Argument doth hold from the Negative, to diſallow what is not found in the Scriptures expreſly, or by good conſequence: As to ſay, ſuch a thing is not expreſſed or revealed in the word; therefore it is no matter of Faith, nor ſuch as a man is bound neceſſarily to believe: ſuch a ſign is not warranted by the Scripture, therefore it is not to be uſed in the Worſhip of God.<note place="margin">Jer. 7.31. &amp; 19.5.</note> Thus the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> reaſoneth more than once againſt the idolatrous men of <hi>Judah,</hi> who burned their Sons and Daughters in the fire to <hi>Baal; The Lord did not command you,</hi> he ſpake no ſuch thing, <hi>neither came it into his mind, Therefore this ye ought not to have done.</hi> The thing he reproved was not onely not commanded, but forbidden, and that expreſly; yet the Prophet chooſeth rather to charge them with the fault of making a Law unto themſelves,<note place="margin">Hook <hi>Eccle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pol.</hi> lib. 2. Sect. 6.</note> than the crime of tranſgreſſing a Law which God had made. For when the Lord himſelf had once preciſely ſet down a form of executing that wherein we are to ſerve him; the fault ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth greater to do that which we are not, than not to do that which we are commanded: In this we ſeem to charge the Law with hardneſs only, in that with fooliſhneſs: In this we ſhew our ſelvs to be weak and unapt to be Doers of his Will, in that we take upon us to be Controllers of his Wiſdom: In this we fly to perform the thing which God ſeeth meet, convenient, and good, in that we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119318:12"/>to ſee what is meeter and convenienter better than God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: For theſe and ſuch like Reaſons, though the ſin of <hi>Judah</hi> was directly prohibited; yet it pleaſed the Lord by his Prophet to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head it, for that he commanded them not ſo to do. From theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſome Divines do prove the perfection of Scripture againſt the Papiſts;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Reynolds.</hi> theſ. <hi>Gatak.</hi> of Lots <hi>cap.</hi> 7. S. 16.</note> Others, that in the Point of God's Worſhip, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holdeth from the Negative for the Subſtance of it: And by the ſame Reaſon we may conclude, that no Ceremony ſignificant may be admitted in the Worſhip of God, which carry not the ſtamp of divine approbation; for the ground of the Prophet's Argument will bear all alike. The purpoſe of God was to teach his People, both unto whom they ſhould offer Sacrifice, and what Sacrifice was to be ſacrificed; therefore no Sacrifice is to be offered which God hath not commanded: The Lord hath determined how he will be ſerved; therefore upon our own Will and Pleaſure we muſt not add any thing unto it for Subſtance, or take ought there-from: And the Lord alſo hath appointed and determined what outward Signes ſhall be uſed to teach, ſignify, or repreſent by Analogy or Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Therefore, no Sign is to have place in his Worſhip, which cannot ſhew deſcent from above:<note place="margin">Numb. 15.38.39.</note> The Lord, expounding the Uſe of the Fringes that he commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to make in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of their Garments, ſaith, <hi>It ſhall be to them for a Sign, that they may look upon it; and remember all the Commandments of the Lord, and do them; and that ye ſeek not after your own hearts, and your own eyes, after which you uſe to go a whoring.</hi> Therefore he willeth, that for ever they remember all his precepts, even thoſe that concern Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or external Worſhip; and on the contrary, he will not that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Ceremonies or external Worſhip they hear their own heart, or inſtitute thoſe things that ſeem good unto them in their own eyes,<note place="margin">Nibil oporteat in rebus divinis facere, ſine Dei Verbo. <hi>Bell. de Sacr. lib. 1. cap. 19.</hi>
               </note> or follow them; Nay, in the Worſhip of God, to follow that which is pleaſing to us, is to run a whoring from God, becauſe we follow them in the heat of adulterous Love. It may be ſome will anſwer, that Ceremonies of abſolute neceſſity, wherein the Subſtance of God's Worſhip conſiſteth, and which abſolutely binds Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, muſt be inſtituted of God; but not thoſe that are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely for ſignification, and as things in themſelves free and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, becauſe theſe may be profitable to put men in mind of their duties to cheriſh Faith, and recall from ſin. But what ground is there in Scripture for this diſtinction; where is the liberty gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119318:12"/>in the one, denied in the other kind of Ceremonies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sicut owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quodcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fuerit extra templum non eſt ſauctificatum.</hi> Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <hi>de</hi> Pont. q. 1. c. 3. &amp; 8. q. 2. c. 2. &amp; q. 4. c 1. S. 2. Orig. <hi>in</hi> Matth. Hom. 25.</note> In Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy no diſtinction is to be allowed, which Reaſon doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm: In Theology, what hath not evident foundation in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themſelves, what is not native and taken out of them, is to be held counterfeit and adulterate: The Rule is, where the Law di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth not, we muſt not diſtinguiſh; it is not ſufficient there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo to diſtinguiſh, unleſs it can be ſhewd (which yet hath not been done) that the diſtinction hath footing in the Word of God. The Papiſts and <hi>Lutherans</hi> do in this manner plead for the Uſe of Images in their Churches; Images are Lay-men's Books, by them they are put in mind of the Death and Paſſion of Chriſt; they may ſee more at once repreſented by them than they can read in many hours. What Anſwer do our Divines return unto them but this, That the Word and Sacraments were appointed of Chriſt to teach,<note place="margin">Conc. Seno. ſenſe. Harm. Conf. Helver. cap. 4. fol. Synt. Tom. 2. l. 6 7. 19. in ſecundo praec. <hi>Par.</hi> in Gen. 28.18. De ſecundo praec. tit. de Imag. c. 15. reſp ad Arg. 9. &amp; 10. Faith cometh by hearing, not by ſeeing or gazing. Jew. art. ador. div. 10. Mart. in 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 7. Gualter in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18.</note> and that to add to them is preſumptuous againſt the Lord, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urious unto his Ordinances; that teaching to the Eye is ſufficiently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Sacraments, and that the Lord, for Inſtruction of his People, commanded his Miniſters to preach, not to paint. Faith, ſaith <hi>Zanchius,</hi> is to be promoted; but by what means, ſuch as God hath ordained, <hi>viz.</hi> The Word and the Sacraments: God would have us to be taught divine things, and all men as well vulgar as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to know things belonging to their Salvation; But whence or of what Inſtructors? Of thoſe that he hath given to be Teachers unto us, not of thoſe that do pleaſe our ſelves: He hath given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us the Book of the Creatures, whence we may know many things of God: He hath given us the Book of the Scripture, which he would have continually to be read, and to be explained in the Church; What canſt thou deſire more? He hath given Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Glaſſes of divine myſteries: He hath inſtituted us a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>arged us to exerciſe our ſelves daily in the Law of God; Ought not theſe Books and Teachers to be ſufficient for us? Now, a ſignificant Ceremony is an Image, or a Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to teach by ſtriking the ſenſe; and what is ſaid againſt Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, muſt neceſſarily hold againſt them alſo; ſo that either we muſt take part with the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and Papiſts againſt the Worthies of our Church, or acknowledge the former diſtinction to be vain, and of none effect. Nay, let this diſtinction be of any weight, and the Papiſts muſt be acquitted in their Oyl, Cream, Salt, Spittle, Croſſes, Lights, Tabers, and the reſt of their rotten Cuſtoms, wherewith they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119318:13"/>have beſmeared and defiled the Ordinances of God; for none of theſe be held by them to be of abſolute neceſſity.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Anſwer there is given to this Argument, of no more ſtrength than the former, <hi>viz.</hi> That to deviſe Signs of ſpirituall things is unwarrantable, but not to ordain Ceremonies that ſhadow forth ſome moral duty which Man oweth to God: But this is barely ſpoken, not proved by any paſſage of holy Writt, and may as eaſily be caſt off as it is brought forth. The Scripture doth not teach it lawful for Man to deviſe myſtical Signs appropriated to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Worſhip of God, to repreſent moral duties; when it forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by any deviſed Sign of that Nature to ſhadow forth ſpiritual duties, and what we learn not thence in matters of this kind, we dare not receive. When the Lord was pleaſed to inſtruct his Church by Types and Figures; he himſelf appointed not onely thoſe that did prefigure Chriſt, but ſuch alſo as ſerved by their ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification to teach moral duties: All myſtical Rites the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf preciſely preſcribed,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.9.38.39. &amp; 39.42.43. 1 Chro. 28.12.19. 2 Chro. 29.25. 1 Chro. 24 19. 2 Chro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.14.</note> laying a ſtrict charge upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> to make all things according to the pattern ſhewed him; which Rule was religiouſly obſerved by all religious and worthy Reformers of Religion afterwards, not one adventuring without ſpecial direction from the Word of God, to add any thing thereto, or alter ought therein.</p>
            <p>Again, Duties moral and ſpiritual are parts of God's inward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and Ceremonies, ordained to teach either of them by myſtical Repreſentation, are parts of his outward Worſhip and Service; and ſo the matter is one, whether the Sign doth ſhaddow forth a morall or ſpiritual duty; for it is not the particular good thing ſignified by the Sign, but the Inſtitution of it to that end, that makes the Worſhip true or falſe: If it be appointed of God, it is true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, let the ſignification be moral or ſpiritual; if of men, it is falſe Worſhip, whatſoever it be ſet a-part to repreſent or teach, in our intention in the ſolemn Worſhip of God. In defence of Images it is objected, that <hi>Paulinus Nolanus</hi> Biſhop commanded the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Old and New Teſtament to be painted in his Church, and that to this end, that the People might be drawn from ſurfetting and drunkenneſs, when they met together to banquet in that place, being buſied in viewing and beholding Images:<note place="margin">See Jewel's Apol. par. 5. cap. 3. div. 1.2.</note> Our Divines re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that the Authority of man ought not to ſeem any thing againſt the plain and manifeſt Word of God; and <hi>Nolanus</hi> and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119318:13"/>did offend the more grievouſly,<note place="margin">Martyr. part. 2. c. 5. S. 23.</note> that they adventured to do that which the former Fathers did alwayes diſallow: whereby we ſee what the judgment of Ancient and Modem Divines is, touching Images ſetup in the Church, to repreſent or put in mind of Moral duties. And if Images muſt be aboliſhed; ſignificant ſigns of mens deviſing, by the ſame reaſon, remain under condemnation: for they are Images, that is, certain figures having relation to the exemplar, or certain pictures with relation of repreſentations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. No Act, Ordinance, nor Inſtitution, contrary to a general Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Commandment, is lawfull, unleſs that Act, Ordinance, or Inſtitution be in ſpecial warranted by the Word of God; for the Scripture ſhould not be ſufficient to make the man of God, that is, the Miniſter or Prophet, perfect to every good work, if an Act in ſpecial might be lawful without particular approbation, which is in general condemned as unjuſt and evill. If we find, that holy men of God did ſome particular things,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 7.17. 1 King 18.32. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 2.5, 6, 7, 13, 14.</note> which were generally forbidden in the Law; as <hi>Samuel</hi> built an Altar at <hi>Ramath, Elias</hi> the Prophet on Mount <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mel;</hi> when by the Law it was not lawfull to offer any Sacrifice, but before the Lord, in the place which he ſhould chuſe. We muſt know, they did this by ſpecial direction, and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary inſtinct. The Lawyers ſay,<note place="margin">Generi per ſpeciem dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur. Sext. de lib. 5. tit. de regulis Juris 33. Digeſt. l. 50. tit. 17. regul. 80.</note> That a particular doth derogate from the general: And in theſe places, where a ſpecial fact doth not agree with a general Precept, there the Scripture is not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant unto it ſelf; but by the ſpecial, it is derogated from the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. But though it was lawfull for them that had ſuch an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Commandment contrary to the Law, at what time it pleaſed God after that manner to make known his pleaſure, to do what was ſo required of them; yet now the reaſon is not like, ſince God ſpeaketh unto us by his Word, according to which we muſt walk and worſhip him, and affordeth not that ſpecial priviledg to us, that he did to them. For God is free, ſubject to no Law;<note place="margin">Zanch. de ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo praec.</note> he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth us, not himſelf; he preſcribeth a general Law, not to himſelf, but to us, which it is never lawful to tranſgreſ, unleſs there be pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar warrant from God for it. But the uſe and inſtitution of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, ſignifying reſemblance in the ſolemn worſhip of God, is contrary to a general Negative Commandment; for the ſecond Commandment forbidding the making of any graven Image, or the likeneſs of any thing in heaven above, or in the earth beneath; doth alſo prohibit all outward forms deviſed by men for Religious uſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119318:14"/>in the ſervice of God: It being a thing peculiar to the Lord, to preſcribe how his will and worſhip ſhall be taught, as what worſhip ſhall be given unto him. By the letter of the Precept onely, the making of graven Images, or Similitudes; and the adoration of them is condemned; but under that particular, we are charged to forge nothing of our own heads, in Ceremonies, or Rites ſignificant, but to be content with thoſe Ceremonies, and that outward Worſhip which God is pleaſed to preſcribe or appoint; whether they be Sacraments, Sacrifices, or other holy things: This to be the ſcope of that Commandment, is made evident many wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by the expoſition that is given thereof in other paſſages of holy Writ: It is an unqueſtionable truth, that the true meaning of every Precept is to be collected out of the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles; and what we find in them commanded or forbidden, is to be referred to ſome one or more of theſe ten Commandments, though it be not expreſly mentioned in any one of them. Now then in the Law we read, That <hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to do all things <hi>according to the pattern ſhewed in the Mount,</hi> without allowance to add <hi>one pin</hi> for reſemblance or ſhadow upon his own head.</p>
            <p>To what Commandment can this charge be referred, but to the ſecond: And muſt it not then condemn all ſignificant Ceremonies forged by men unto themſelves for the ſervice of God; <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> are ſmitten with death,<note place="margin">Levit. 10.1. Numb. 3.4. Lev. 1.7. &amp; 6.12. &amp; 9.24. Piſc. obſ. in Lev. 10.2.</note> for preſuming to offer with <hi>ſtrange fire,</hi> which God commanded not; whence Divines obſerve, that the external worſhip of God is preciſely to be exerciſed according to the Preſcription of God; and that we may not depart one hair breadth from his holy Inſtitution upon any good intent; this their fact was contrary to the ſecond Commandment; and is it not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt then that we are thereby enjoyned, neither to alter what God hath inſtituted, nor to deviſe of our own heads what he never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. What Precept did <hi>Ahaz</hi> tranſgreſs in commanding an Altar for burnt offering to be made after the pattern of the Altar at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> but the ſecond? or by what reaſon can it be reduced un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, unleſs we ſhall acknowledg that all things appointed by God in his ſervice, muſt carefully be obſerved without addition or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, and that all devices of men for worſhip, and inſtruction, are utterly unlawfull.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The words of the Commandment do ſhew no leſs;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119318:14"/>for the former word <hi>Peſel</hi> doth ſignify any thing hewen, graven,<note place="margin">Deut. 7.5. &amp; 2.3. Deut. 7.25. Eſay 16.17. Hoſ. 13.2. Ezek, 8.10. Deut. 27.15. Eſay 30.22. Numb. 12.8. Pſal. 17.15.</note> cut or carved; which is tranſlated by the Greek, an Idoll; the <hi>Caldee</hi> Paraphraſe, an Image; and the <hi>Thargum,</hi> called <hi>Jonathans,</hi> an Image or figure; under which name, all other ſorts are implyed, as Molten or Painted Images, or the like. The other word <hi>Tema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> is in ſignification, a ſimilitude or figure, and is opened by <hi>Moſes,</hi> by <hi>Semel,</hi> and <hi>Tabinth,</hi> words of the ſame ſignification, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.16. So that all Portrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures, Shapes, Reſemblances, and Forms of things, Natural, or Artificial, Real, or Imaginary, devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by man for Religious uſe, worſhip, or inſtruction, are forbidden both by the ſcope, and letter of the Commandment. And if the words were not of that large ſignification, yet ſeeing all vices of the ſame kind are forbidden where one is expreſly mentioned; when material, cut or carved Images are prohibited, there all repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenrations, material, aerial, real, imaginary, proper, and tropical, are condemned; For it is not the matter of the thing, but the form or application that is againſt the Precept, which is one and the ſame in repreſentations of what kind ſoever, in Pictures, proper, Meto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymical, and Metaphorical: It matters not whether the Image be a thing truly exiſtent, formed of any viſible matter, Braſs, Wood, or Stone; or whether it have no other being but in the mind of men. If it be an Image deviſed by men for Religious uſe, it commeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſentence of the Law:<note place="margin">Martin de Sac. tract. 5. cap. 6.</note> if we ask the conſent of learned In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, they generally agree herein. Thus they reaſon againſt the Image of the Crucifix ſtamped upon the Popiſh hoaſt: the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Law of God diſalloweth all Images made for the cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, after what ſort ſoever; but Chriſt crucified ſet before our eyes in the Word and Sacraments, is life and Salvation. When our Adverſaries alledg in defence of Images, That <hi>Solomon</hi> in his Temple erected Cherubims on the Mercy-ſeat, where God was worſhipped: To this our Divines anſwer,<note place="margin">Abbot againſt Biſhop. tract of Imag. SS. 8. Will. Cont. 9. q. r. Art. 2. alſo the ſecond Anſw.</note> That theſe Cherubims were erected by the ſpecial Commandment of God, who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed both the form of them, and the place where they ſhould be ſet. For God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to make the Ark, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory or Mercy-ſeat, which was the Cover of the Ark, according to the faſhion that he had ſhewed him: withal, he appointed him to make two Cherubims, one at the one end of the Mercy-ſeat, and the other at the other end; ſo that with their wings ſtretched out, they ſhould cover the Mercy-ſeat. According to this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119318:15"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> did, but what was done with theſe Cherubims which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet up, it is uncertain; but this is moſt ſure, that <hi>Solomon</hi> by vertue of the ſame Commandment,<note place="margin">1 Reg. 8.5, 6.</note> and to obſerve that which by <hi>Moſes</hi> was preſcribed, made two <hi>Cherubims</hi> to ſtand in the ſame place, as the other did, and to the ſame uſe. Inaſmuch then as God had by the Law directed in what ſort this ſhould be done, <hi>Solomon</hi> needed no further ſpecial direction for the doing of it, but had Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed againſt God, if, being appointed to build an houſe unto God, he had not done it according to ſuch rules as the Law before had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for the doing of it. It is fitly anſwered (ſaith <hi>Martyr</hi>) That God gave the Law,<note place="margin">Com. places, part, 2. cap. 5. S. 26.</note> not to himſelf, but unto us; ſo then we muſt follow the ſame, neither may we bring him into order; if he other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles would do any thing of ſpecial Prerogative, he muſt be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do after his own will, but we muſt obey the Law that is made. Thoſe ſpecial Precepts of God (ſaith <hi>Urſinus</hi>) did as much derogate from the ſecond Commandment concerning Images,<note place="margin">Urſin. tom. de Imag. pag. 43.</note> as that ſingular Commandment in times paſt given unto <hi>Abraham</hi> concerning the offering of his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> may be ſaid to have detracted from the ſixth Precept of the Decalogue.<note place="margin">Tert. de Idolat.</note> Of old, <hi>Tertullian</hi> returned the ſame Anſwer to the like Objection; <q>Well and good, (ſaith he) one and the ſame God, both by his general Law forbad any Image to be made, and alſo by his extraordinary and ſpeciall Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, willed an Image of a Serpent to be made; If thou be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the ſame God, thou haſt his Law, Make no Image; but if thou have regard to the Image of the Serpent that was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward made by <hi>Moſes,</hi> then do thou as <hi>Moſes</hi> did. Make not any Image againſt the Law, unleſs God command thee, as he did <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>They add further, that they were types of ſpiritual things; which now have not place in the Church of God: Certainly (ſaith <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi>) theſe Images had ſome figurative meaning:<note place="margin">Ubi ſupra.</note> But they were not ſet forth, as an example for us to follow; and ſeeing they were external things, and had the Word added to them, they were (after a ſort) Sacraments of thoſe times: and it is only God, and not man, that can make Sacraments. And in Concluſion, they ſhut up their Anſwer with this,<note place="margin">Martin. de 2. praec. pag. 166. Martyr. ubi ſupra.</note> That we muſt attempt nothing without the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement and Warrant of God: For it is to be noted, That <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> which made the Cherubins, durſt not make any other, they only made that, which was commanded unto them by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119318:15"/>God: They painted not upon the Walls the acts of <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor the doings of <hi>Adam, Moſes,</hi> or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers of the Fathers. By all this they ſufficiently declare, That, in their judgments, the erecting of Images in the Temple for ſignification only, without ſpeciall War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from God, is a breach and violation of the holy Law and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> tom. 2. de diviſ. decalog. Fulk Rejoyn. againſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial. Perk. Arm. aurea. Martin. ubi ſupra. Lumb. l. 4. diſt. 1. T. Aquin. pag. 3. q. 83. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 1. Jewels Apol. Angl. pag. 37.</note> And in their Expoſitions upon this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, they teach, That it condemneth all counterfeit means of Gods Worſhip, and requireth the obſervation of Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies preſcribed by the Lord; in which only we ought to reſt: For it becomes us not to think our ſelves wiſer than God; who would not have his Church to be inſtructed with dumb ſigns, but with the lively preaching of the Word: The Sacraments are Images in the eyes of all the Learned, and unlawful by this Commandement, had not God himſelf commanded them. What? Are they unlawfull only as ſeals, and not as viſible ſigns of God's Will and Pleaſure? Yes; as ſigns alſo; for a ſign ſignifying by reſemblance, and an Image, are equivalent, and in largeneſs of ſenſe but one; and a ſign is a ſign from him that hath a power to inſtitute it. The affirmative part enjoyneth obedience to all the Worſhip appointed by God; all which was ſignificative, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. &amp; 8.1. But by the nature of the affirmative, we learn: Therefore we may conclude, that the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of ſignificant Ceremonies, is directly contrary to the Moral Law of God; and, without his warrant, is utterly unlawful.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The quality of the Negative.</hi> Nullum enim ſignum ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poteſt eſſe cauſa gratiae, nec illam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibiliter ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare, niſi ex Domini inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutione. <hi>Bell.</hi> de Sac. l. 1. c. 11. Atqui in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentis ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificare gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam eſt eid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Sacramentali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conferre. <hi>Chem.</hi> de Sac. l. 3. c. 8.</note>4. <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin:</hi> But ſignificant Ceremonies not approved of God in his Word, cannot be inſtituted or uſed in faith. Man hath a twofold light given him for his guidance and direction, Natural Reaſon; and Super-natural Inſtruction; and what cannot be determined by the former, muſt be warranted by the other; otherwiſe it is unlawful, and conſequently not of Faith: But natural reaſon cannot determine what Ceremonies ſignificant are meet and fit to be uſed in the ſolemn Worſhip of God: For man hath neither power nor authority to bleſs, nor liberty to annex any ſuch forged or deviſed ſigns to the holy Inſtitution, nor wiſdom to diſcern what is fit and acceptable in that kind. He that is of authority to inſtitute a ſign to be the teacher of my underſtanding, and an inciter of my devotion, muſt be able to give vertue inherent, or aſſiſtance to that which ſhould be the cauſe of ſuch effects; elſe is the ſign vain and fruitleſs, the deviſer idle and preſumptuous. Now, man of himſelf can give no power to any Symbolical ſign of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119318:16"/>hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deviſing,<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tte n. breg. tit. de conſecrat. aquae ſalis. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtyr. <hi>Com. Places.</hi> p. 4. c. 9. Sect. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un. de cult. Sanct. l. 3. c. 7. n. 12.</note> to produce ſuch effects: For the vertue of things comes either from the Word of God put forth in the firſt Creation, or from his after-inſtitution, or from the Churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpetration; which obtaineth by prayer thoſe effects of things to which they ſerve by God's Creation and Inſtitution; not any creating or new conception of things to ſupernatural uſes: So that what force or vertue to ends or purpoſes ſupernatural, God hath not p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t into the creature, that, man by his inſtitution, cannot communicate unto it. Things natural, have indeed by creation an aptneſs in them to repreſent ſpiritual; and ſome agreement with them: But the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of them to this purpoſe, the bleſſing of them in this uſe, is from Him only that gave them their firſt being. Man cannot give any bleſſing to his deviſes;<note place="margin">Zepp. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. l. 3. c. 12. <hi>Greg.</hi> 2.</note> Nor hath he any warrant to begg Gods bleſſing upon them: for God will not be effectual by Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or humane Ceremonies, but by the order and mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appointed by Himſelf;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tth.</hi> 15.8.</note> according to that, <hi>They worſhip me in vain by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of men:</hi> Therefore ſuch humane ceremonies can work no true devotion, no motions of heart pleaſing to God, no confirmation of faith, or ſerious repentance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but only have an opinion of wiſdome in voluntary worſhip.<note place="margin">Col. 2.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Again: What underſtanding is there in man, to aſſure him that he may lawfully annex ſigns of his own deviſing to the Word and Sacraments, which God hath ordained for the full inſtruction of his Church?<note place="margin">Levi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.1. Deut. 1.18. &amp; 17.3. 1 Reg. 16.14. 2 Reg. 17.26.</note> God hath diſallowed the inſtitution of new rites not commanded: as <hi>Achaz</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> building new Altars in the houſe of the Lord, are reprehended for it. And is there any wit of man that can deviſe how we ſhould follow them in that kind; or in general do as they did; and not incurre the ſame rebuke? As the ſin of the Angels that fell, and the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> was one in kind, though different in its ſpecial nature; So is the ſin of building an Altar, and deviſing Sacramental rites in the worſhip of God. Is it not our duty to acknowledg God ſo wiſe and gracious in the ſigns that he hath choſen; as to hold it preſumption for any man to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare him in deviſing of the like? Are not the Sacraments the ſeals of the heavenly King? and can any new print be added to the ſeal of a King, without high Treaſon? What Maſter of a Family in his houſe, What Prince in his Dominion, would grant power to any one, to change, alter, or reform any thing upon his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? The ſigns which the Lord hath inſtituted for the inſtruction
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119318:16"/>of his Church, are ſufficient, and do better ſerve for the purpoſe than any that man can deviſe: Therefore it is needleſs to forge any other; yea, it is a vilifying of the wiſdom of God. It is eaſie to ſhew, that the godly Learned in all Ages have diſliked the devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of new ſigns; howſoever, who men they have failed in ſome particulars, and ignorantly gone againſt what in general they ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught: He is too partiall, as will not acknowledg this in the Fathers themſelves, who did ſubſtantially maintain the perfection of Scripture, and the neceſſity of celebrating Divine Myſteries ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preciſe inſtitution delivered unto them: and yet gave more power and vertue to vain inventions, and urged the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Traditions, further than the Truth would permit; or can ſtand with their own doctrine and poſitions truly laid down in other places of their Writings. It is well known, the Papiſts have mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>upted the Simplicity of Gods Ordinances, by their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, vain, and idle Ceremonies; yet ſome ſparkles of this truth doth ſhine amongſt them: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would prove, that the Jews did not only deſire a corporal ſign of the true God,<note place="margin">De Eccl. trimuph. l. 2. c. 13. Sect. <hi>At hoc.</hi>
               </note> becauſe then they had no need to make a Calf; for they had a Cloud and a Pillar, which did lead them better than the Calf, which muſt be carried: In this reaſon, though weak and ſimple (for humane vanity doth many things both needleſs, and unlawful; elſe had their Oyl, Cream, Salt, Spittle, <hi>Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Dei,</hi> never been deviſed) this truth is contained, That where God hath ordained ſigns profitable and ſufficient for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of his Church,<note place="margin">Si populo Ch iſtiano Apoſtoli Caere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monias vel Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus divinitus traditos impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere noluerunt; quis, oro, ſanae mentis obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det illi adin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventiones ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inventas hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitus. Confeſs. Hel. vet. cap. 27. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb. tit. de Baptiſ. Calv. opuſc. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 59.</note> It is needleſs and vain for men to deviſe and conſtitute others, or more, for that end and purpoſe. Again, the Ceremonies which were ordained by God himſelf, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of his Church by their ſignification, are now ceaſed; and cannot be continued without ſin: and what warrant then hath any man, upon his own will and pleaſure to inſtitute or ordain ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Ceremonies in the time of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>When the Church was an Infant, kept under the Rudiments of the Law, ſhe was to be taught onely by thoſe ſhadows and figures that God preſcribed: And now, in the brightneſs of the Goſpel when all figures, ſhadows, vail, adumbrations; whether ſignifying things preſent or to come, be done away: Shall we think the light of reaſon ſufficient to direct, without the guidance of Scripture in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tters of Rites and Ceremonies, appropriated to the ſolemn Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God for the Inſtruction of his People? Were the old fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119318:17"/>taken away,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> de Pont. Rom. q. 7. c. 3. Art. 6. Idem. cont. Dura. l. 9. Sect. 59. p. 826. <hi>Rainold.</hi> Conf. with H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt. c. 8. d. 4. p. 50. lin. 30. <hi>Viſin.</hi> tom. 2. tit. de Imag. 1 Cor. 11.23. Mat. 28.19, 28. Acts 10.47. <hi>Whitak.</hi> cont. Dur. Lib. 5. Sect. 21. &amp; l. 10. Sect. 21. &amp; l. 8. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 65.</note> that there might be place for new? Were Divine aboliſhed, that Humane might ſucceed? Well then, may our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries triumph over the Forces that are ſent forth againſt their Superſtitions; burdenſome, Jewiſh, vain, and heatheniſh Rites and Cuſtoms. Our Writers diſpute thus againſt them: We muſt have no other ſigns in Baptiſm, than ſuch as the Scripture warranteth; They alledge that of the Apoſtle, <hi>What I have received of the Lord, that do I deliver;</hi> That of our Saviour, <hi>Go and Baptize, teaching them to obſerve whatſoever I command you;</hi> That of <hi>Peter, Can any forbid Water that theſe may not be Baptized;</hi> And generally, the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: But if Cerimonies ſignificant be lawfull, which have onely Warrant or Approbation from the will or wit of Man; then muſt all theſe reaſons ſtoop to the Oyl, Cream, Salt, Lights, and Spittle, in uſe amongſt them; for all theſe have as much reaſon and ſhew of Wiſdom to Warrant them, as any other can that are ſimply of man's deviſing: And, what Underſtanding or Judgment can man have of himſelf to diſcern how, or by what means God will be Worſhipped? None at all. For the Scripture teſtifieth that every man is brutiſh by his own knowledge,<note place="margin">Jer. 10.14, &amp; 51, 17.</note> nor more able to diſcern what in this caſe is fit and acceptable, than a blind man is to judge of Colours;<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20. Jer. 8.9.</note> that there is no light in them that ſpeak not according to the Scripture, no wiſdom in them that reject the Word of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There is a certain light engraven in the hearts of men by Nature, whereby they know ſomewhat concerning God; as, that there is a God, that he is wiſe, juſt, good and bountiful, the Governour of all things; and they diſcern ſome things pertaining to juſtice, equity, temperance, honeſt commerce and dealing with men: but they are utterly ignorant how, or by what means God will be ſerved, what he will bleſs for the Inſtruction of his People. We ſee and know by experience, That is moſt perillous, unprofitable, and diſallowed of God, that doth beſt ſort with our vain concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Carnal Obſervations,<note place="margin">Col. 2.23.</note> ſuch as, <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not;</hi> have a ſhew of wiſdom in voluntary Religion, and carry a glorious ſhew of holineſſe to our ſeeming; when the Word of God diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth them to be fruitleſs, diſtaſtfull, odious. Whence grew the firſt contempt of God's Ordinances, the pollution of holy things with carnall Cuſtoms, that are according to this World; and not according to godlineſſe; the corruptions of the Truth with manifold Superſtitions and Idolatries; but from a fond admiration of Rites
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119318:17"/>and Cuſtoms deviſed by others, or taken up upon our own Heads; which being once admitted into the Worſhip of God, did multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and increaſe till they had obſcured, if not clean covered and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed the ſimplicity and glory of God's Ordinances, (as bad weeds overgrow the Corn) and ſecretly ſtollen the heart away from all due reverence and reſpect to the word of Life, and ſeals of our Salvation. For as a man is blind, carnall, impotent; and yet a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of his own devices: So are the ſigns deviſed by him, dark, vailing the brightneſs of the Goſpel; carnall, not ſpirituall; dead without Power; and yet better affected, more delighted in, than the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelves. No ſooner was the ſign of the Croſs added un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Baptiſm, and made a ſign like to the Lord's; but it preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came greater than the Water which was Chriſt's ſign, and that in the Eyes of them who ſo advanced it. Moreover, admit Reaſon for an Umpire in this matter, and Images cannot be kept out of the Church: for no means is more profitable to inform the mind, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the memory, and move the affection, than is the ſight of a Picture artificially made, cut, or carved; if a man may believe himſelf, or give credit to his immagination: If the Will of God be not unto us inſtead of all reaſons, we ſhall be hardly drawn to diſlike that manner of teaching or worſhipping. A man that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with the knowledge of God's Will, and the myſtery of Salvation; may lawfully in his meditations make uſe of diverſe Creatures or things, that are apt and fit to repreſent Spirituall things unto him: but he muſt not take upon him to determine them to be uſed as ſigns for ſuch an end and purpoſe; for having no promiſe of God to come by that courſe, he can expect no bleſſing from God in that practice, but the contrary: Seeing therefore man is himſelf ignorant and unwiſe, neither able to receive the things of the Spirit, nor diſcern that which pertaineth to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt; (nor yet being enlightned with the knowledge of the Truth according to godlineſſe, to deviſe any fit or acceptable means whereby God ſhould be worſhipped, or his People taught in the wayes of holineſs): It followeth, That in the worſhip of God, ſigns not approved of him in his Word, cannot be inſtituted or uſed in Faith, and conſequently are to be held unlawfull.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Chriſt Jeſus, the great Doctor of his Church,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.8, 10. Joh. 4.25. Acts 1.3.</note> being called of his heavenly Father to teach to us perfectly, and at once, the whole Counſell of God, and the things that did pertain to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119318:18"/>Kingdom of God to the end of the World, was faithfull in all his Houſe, as was <hi>Moſes;</hi> and made known unto his Diſciples what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he received of his Father.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.2, 5.</note> But <hi>Moſes</hi> preſcribed the form of God's worſhip in every particular Ceremony ſignificant; and brought in none,<note place="margin">Joh. 15.15.</note> no not one into the Church, which the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did not inſtitute, giving charge to the Church of the Jews, That the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould neither add thereto,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.9, 38, 39, 40, &amp; 27 19, &amp; 39, 42 43. Deut. 12, 32.</note> nor take ought therefrom. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Saviour Chriſt alſo taught his Diſciples what Ceremonies ſignificant ought to be uſed in the Church of God, to whoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance nothing muſt be added, from whoſe Inſtitution nothing ought to be diminiſhed: The old Teſtament was indeed delivered unto one People only of the World; The Commiſſion of the Goſpel was, <hi>Go teach all Nations.</hi> But the liberty of Inſtituting Rites ſignificant was no greater to the Chriſtian Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Viſ. Jun.</hi> Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mad. in Bell. lib. 4. de pont. Cap. 17.</note> than to the Church of the Jews: They had a preſcription of particular Ceremonies, moſt fitly agreeing to the polity of their Church and Common-wealth, and diſpenſation of thoſe times: So, hath the Chriſtian Church alſo: to which we are as preciſely bound, as ever was the Church of the Jews to the Ordinances appointed for that time and ſtate, as hath been ſhewed before; in Circumſtantiall matters concerning Time, Place, and Order of divine Service; And ſeveral Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches have liberty according to the generall Rules of Scripture to conſtitute what is moſt agreeable to the condition of the Country, and doth beſt tend to Edification: And in theſe things the Jews had Authority no leſs than the others. In Ceremonies and Rites ſignificant annexed to the Worſhip of God, the Jews were tyed to the written Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets; nor may any thing be attempted lawfully by the Chriſtian Church in things of this Nature, more than was or ought to have been by them. Though men be as different almoſt in Nature as in Nations and Languages, yet muſt they of neceſſity ſubmit themſelves to the uſe of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, which two Ceremonies onely are commanded by Divine precept; and are to be received of all Chriſtians, that in truth and ſoundneſs profeſſe the Goſpel. And ſeeing Chriſt Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted no ſigns but theſe, the Apoſtles commended no other to the ſeverall Churches planted and dreſſed by them: What neceſſity is there, that difference of People to which the Goſpel is now preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhould inferr a liberty of inventing new Signs or Rites never ſeen or allowed of Chriſt? Thoſe that God preſcribed for the Jews
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119318:18"/>were fit for that Time, and for that People, none elſe might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed; thoſe that Chriſt hath ordained for all Churches are ſufficient; moſt fit for them; what ſhall be brought in beſides and annexed to them, doth want both his Approbation and Bleſſing: As <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull in the Houſe of God <hi>as a Servant,</hi> both in thing: re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll and rituall, as ſome diſtinguiſh; So was Chriſt alſo, <hi>as a Son,</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did his faithfulneſs ſtand in removing the Law of Jewiſh Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and disburdening all Chriſtians from the uſe of them; but in preſcribing Laws and Ordinances, whereby the Church is to be ordered and inſtructed untill his ſecond coming, and that as particularly and expreſly as <hi>Moſes</hi> had done unto the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> To ſtand upon compariſon betwixt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in perfection or reall faithfulneſs, (as ſome call it) is not to this purpoſe; for his perfection is one thing, his faithfulneſſe another: and whom He did exceed in perfectneſſe, He did every way equalize in faithfulneſſe in the Houſe of God: He did not onely teach a more excellent Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine than <hi>Moſes,</hi> but more full and perfect: He did not onely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquate what Ceremonies were to be ſhadows of good things to come, and figures of man's Redemption by his Sacrifice upon the Croſſe; but he ordained alſo, with what viſible Signs and Tokens his Church ſhould be nourtured, and aſſured of his love and favour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> As he died to bring Life to mankind, raiſed up himſelf from Death, aſcended, entred within the Vail, and hath taken poſſeſſion of the heavenly Manſion; for us: So did he give direction to his Apoſtles, and in them to all Churches, by what Statutes and Laws his People ſhould be Governed, by what Signs and Ceremonies they ſhould be taught and confirmed in Faith. Do we then leave nothing to the Arbitrament of the Church? Nothings but what was left to the Power and Authority of the Jewiſh Church: for we have a Canon as perfect, a direction as exact and particular as ever they had. Many honourable witneſſes of God's truth have judiciouſly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That Chriſt in holy Scripture hath not ſingularly and ſpecially preſcribed concerning externall Diſcipline and Ceremonies; for that he foreſaw theſe things were to depend upon the occaſions and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of times, which muſt be determined by generall Rules given for direction in theſe caſes; whoſe Judgment we imbrace with reverence, &amp; acknowledg conſonant to the words of wholeſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſo it be underſtood according to their true intent and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Of matters meetly accidentall, circumſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iall, or naturall
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119318:19"/>concerning Diſcipline or Worſhip: But thence to infer a liberty to ordain in ſubſtantial matters of Diſcipline &amp; ſignificative Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies whatſoever ſhall ſeem good in our own eys, without the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and warrant of Gods Word, is more than the Learned grant, or the Truth it ſelf will permit: As touching the Church (ſaith <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi>) ſhe altereth not her form.<note place="margin">Loc. Com. part. 1. c. 11. Sect. 12.</note> It is alwayes one manner of Common wealth, &amp; nothing is hid from the underſtanding of God the Author of the Laws. The Lord of the houſe was not inferiour to the ſervant in fidelity: What our Saviour Chriſt heard and ſaw of the Father; that he manifeſted to his Diſciples, charging them to teach the Church to obſerve it: What they received of the Lord, that they delivered in great ſimplicity, without any addition of new doctrine to his Doctrine, or of deviſed ſymbolical ſigns to his Signs; never once intimating in their Epiſtles or Writings, any liberty that the Church ſhould have to multiply Rites or Ceremonies for myſticall ſignification, and to annex them to the holy things of God. And when we can neither hear from <hi>Moſes,</hi> Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, that the forging and inventing of ſuch obſervations is allowed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; what warrant can we have to bear us out therein? If Cities and Towns-Corporate plead Immunities and Exemptions from the Law, and aſſume to themſelves authority to make Decrees of this or that ſort: being impleaded by the King's Attorney for it; either they muſt ſhew their Charter to warrantize ſuch Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, or incur Cenſure for their ſawcineſs and preſumption: So they that challenge priviledg to deviſe ſignificant Rites in the Worſhip of God, and annex them to the Signs which God Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath eſtabliſhed, muſt either ſhew their Charter ſigned with the authentique Seal of the Court of Heaven, or be caſt in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when they be impleaded at his Barr.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If God be the only Teacher of his Church to inſtruct it by Word and Sign, then no Ceremonies ſignificant may be admitted into the ſolemn Worſhip of God for doctrine and inſtruction, but ſuch as bear his ſtamp, are marked with his Seal, are warranted by holy Scripture: For the chaſte Spouſe of Chriſt, who knowes the voyce of her Beloved, will not acknowledg unwritten Traditions for the Word of God: But God is the only Teacher of his Church both by Word and Sign.<note place="margin">Jam. 4.12. Matth. 23.8. Act. 3.32.</note> As the doctrine which is taught muſt be from above, ſo the means whereby it is taught muſt be of God: both he that teacheth new doctrines, and he that deviſeth ſtrange
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119318:19"/>means to inſtruct the people of God in the knowledg of the truth according to godlineſs, doth run upon his own head.<note place="margin">Mic. 7.16. Hoſ. 14.1.</note> It is a truth without controverſie; That as to forgive ſins, receive into favour, and bleſs with ſpiritual bleſſings in Jeſus Chriſt, is proper to the Lord alone; ſo it is his peculiar,<note place="margin">Eſay 7.14. &amp; 38.7.</note> to inſtitute ſigns and ſeals of his Covenant and Mercy. For none can ſign a Leaſe, who hath not power to let and demiſe it: nor annex a ſeal to any promiſe, that hath not authority to make it, and to confer the good promiſed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jewel.</hi> Treat. of the Sacr.</note> But it ſeems as lawful to deviſe new ſeals of Divine promiſes, as Symbolical ſigns of ſpiritual duties: ſeeing to teach the way to heaven, and to preſcribe what ſervice man ſhould perform to God; doth belong to him that hath Power and Soveraignty of life and death, who is able to ſave and to deſtroy. And if we may be bold to invent ſigns to teach man his duty; and link them to the means of God's Worſhip, ſo long as they ſignifie no other thing but what the Scripture teacheth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar.</hi> de Sacr. l. 1. cap. 24. Sect. de Sacr.</note> Why may we not bring in ſigns alſo to aſſure us of the truth of Gods promiſes, when nothing is thereby aſſured and ſealed, but what is promiſed in the written Word. As the Duty taught, and the Promiſe confirmed, are both from one Supream; ſo the ſign of Inſtruction, and the ſeal of Confirmation, do challenge the ſame authour, require the ſame authority. This will the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appear, if we ſhall conſider, That ſigns do not become ſeals by any ſpecial inſtitution; whereby they are diſtinguiſhed from ſigns in regard of the efficient cauſe, but in reſpect of the thing that they are appointed to ſign or ſignifie: Signs of Divine promiſes are ſeals, true or falſe; vain or behooveful, even from this, that they are determined to ſignifie ſuch a thing, whether the Inſtitution be of God or Man. Signs of mans duty, be ſigns only, from what authour ſoever they have their ordination. The reaſon is, becauſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are only taught, not aſſured as duties; but promiſes repreſented by ſigns are thereby ſealed. What is a ſeal,<note place="margin">Baſting. Cate. q. 66. of the Sacram.</note> but a ſign ſealing up a thing promiſed; or a print whereby a thing promiſed by Covenant is ſigned. Therefore if the Church may not preſume to add new ſeals to the promiſes of God, but is bound to reſt contented with them that are commended unto her by the Lord himſelf, She may not deviſe ſymbolical ſigns in the worſhip of God, for the inſtruction of her children in the wayes of holineſs. It may further be added, That a ſign is a viſible word: and therefore if no voyce muſt be heard in the Congregation but the Lords alone; no teaching ſigns
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119318:20"/>muſt be admitted in his worſhip, but ſuch as he hath licenſed to ſpeak and ſtand in place.<note place="margin">Syntag tom. 2. l. 6. c. 38.</note> 
               <hi>Polanus</hi> ſaith, Thoſe things are impious, which are directly oppoſed to the Commandement of God; of which ſort are many Traditions of the Papiſts; as, the abuſe of the Lords Supper, the Maſs, Invocation of dead men, worſhipping of Images, the law concerning Single life, Feſtival dayes dedicated to Saints, Images made for religious uſes, that is, that they might ſerve for the uſe of Religion, either that they might be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, or that holy things might be repreſented by them, or that God be worſhipped by them: For God willeth not this end of Images, but will have all men taught by his Word; <hi>Monumenta autem quibus res divinae repreſentantur ſunt ſola Sacramenta, non picta, aut ficta, aut ſculpta, ſed adminiſtrata et uſurpata legitimè</hi> In the Book of Homilies,<note place="margin">Hom. for <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſontide,</hi> part. 2. <hi>Fulk</hi> againſt <hi>Rhem.</hi> in Luc. 24. Sect. 5.</note> all humane deviſed ſigns are condemned in Baptiſm, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no ſigns ſhould burden the Church, ſave thoſe which the Lord hath left, which are not burdenſome. D. <hi>Fulk</hi> demandeth of the <hi>Rhemiſts,</hi> How is the ſign of the Croſſe a convenient me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of Chriſt's death, which is not ordained of Chriſt, nor taught by the Apoſtles to be ſuch?<note place="margin">Cont. Bell. de cult. Sanct. l. 3. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Lambertus Danaus</hi> is reſolure; It is blaſphemy (ſaith he) to think that any outward thing may be made a ſign in the Church of any thing that is ſpiritual; unleſſe it be expreſly ordained in the Word, and commanded by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be uſed to that end. <hi>Bucer</hi> condemneth them that deviſe any ſign for religious uſe: And this the Schoolmen themſelves ſaw and taught: It pertaineth only to the ſignifier to determine what ſigns muſt be uſed to ſignifie.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Scripture is the ſole and ſufficient Rule of all immediate worſhip,<note place="margin">Levit. 10.1. Jer. 7.31. Deut. 12.31, 32. Col. 2.23.</note> internal or external, moral or ceremonial, as it is evident by the whole tenour of Gods Word, and the general Confeſſion of all Proteſtant Divines. The Lord never left it to the will and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrament of man, to worſhip him as ſeemed good in his own eyes: But in all Ages of the World, and ſtates of the Church, he ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed how he would be ſerved. The duty that <hi>Adam</hi> owed in the ſtate of Innocency, muſt be paid according to the preſcription: he was taught in what he ſhould ſhew his obedience, what time he ſhould ſet apart as a ſolemn day of reſt; the like may be ſaid of all the worſhip he was to perform. After the Fall, Was any worſhip al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, which was not commanded? We read not of any expreſs Commandement that the Fathers had to offer Sacrifice, or to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119318:20"/>the difference of clean and unclean beaſts. But without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, they received particular inſtructions from the Lord, touching theſe things, either by the inſpiration of his Spirit, or ſome Word, or both: For the Scripture ſaith, <hi>God had reſpect unto</hi> Abel, <hi>and his ſacrifice:</hi> But ſacrifice and burnt-offerings could not pleaſe him,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.4, 5. Pſal. 50.9, 10. Heb. 11.7. Heb. 11.6.</note> if they had not been offered in faith and obedience. Again, <hi>By faith</hi> Abel <hi>offered a greater ſacrifice then</hi> Cain; <hi>without which it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to pleaſe God.</hi> But faith preſuppoſeth revelation, and obedience a Commandement. In other Ages of the Church it is moſt clear and evident, that the Lord ſhewed to his Church the whole form of worſhip, wherewith for that time he would be ſerved, unto which they might not add; from which they might not detract the leaſt jot or tittle. The Prophets, our Saviour Chriſt, the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Levit. 10.1. Jer. 7.31. &amp; 28.14.47. &amp; 12.30. &amp; 29.26. &amp; 31.20. Exod. 20.5. &amp; 10.26. &amp; 12.30. Judg. 10.10. 2 Sam. 16.19. 2 Reg. 10.18, 19, 21, 22. &amp; 17.33. &amp; 21.28. 1 Chr. 28.19. 2 Chro. 30.23. Jer. 8.2. Mal. 3.14, 15. Rainold. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſ. Apoc. tom. 2. p. 244.</note> do ſharply reprehend all Rites deviſed by man for religious uſe, though carrying never ſo great a ſhew of wiſdom, humility and care: which they would never have done, if will-worſhip had not been unlawful, and diſpleaſing unto God. To ſpend many words in the confimation of this Point is ſuperfluous, ſince it is a truth generally received by all Proteſtant Divines, That Ceremonies are unlawful, when they be impoſed, urged, or uſed with opinion of holineſs, neceſſity or worſhip. But to prevent miſtaking, it will be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient here to ſhew, what Worſhip is, and what warrant each part thereof muſt have from God. The Hebrew word, <hi>Habad,</hi> which ſignifies to Serve, is commonly uſed for all that ſervice, good and bad, which is given either to the true God, or Idols: which two kinds of worſhip as they agree in one common nature of Worſhip or Service, ſo do they in their general or common nature, though they be oppoſite in their ſpecial nature, objects, and adjuncts: contraries we know muſt conſent in ſome third, as vertue and vice, hot and cold, black and white: the ſame is to be held of Divine worſhip true and falſe. For ſervice comprehending under it worſhip true and falſe, as the parts thereof, at leaſt analogical; of neceſſity the common nature of worſhip muſt agree to them both, elſe how could the ſervice of Idols, or falſe-worſhip of the true God, be called Worſhip: This hath been wiſely obſerved in other caſes not unlike, by our learned Writers againſt the common Adverſary. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would prove, That the offering of Incenſe and ſweet Odours, is not a Sacrifice in the New Teſtament; becauſe it is not offered by the Prieſt only, nor only to the Lord. Our Divines reply, That there are many Sacrifices, to which that definition of Sacrifices cannot
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119318:21"/>agree, <hi>viz.</hi> prophane Sacrifices which are offered by them that are no Prieſts; to devils, and not to God; after a manner deviſed, not preſcribed by God: and therefore ſeeing that of Sacrifices ſome be holy, and ſome prophane, in the definition of a ſacrifice in general, thoſe things only are to be put, which are common to both kinds. In like manner, when there is a true and falſe worſhip; an holy and prophane ſervice, thoſe things only are to be put in the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of worſhip, which agree to both kinds. Divine worſhip taken in that latitude of ſenſe as to comprehend the ſervice of God true and falſe, (for to ſpeak of the worſhip of falſe gods, is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent) is an action or work commanded by Divine Authority, inſtituted by man, or deviſed upon our own heads, whereby God is worſhipped, his promiſes are ſealed; or obedience to his Will is taught.<note place="margin">Zanch. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demp. in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum prec. Par. dradiaph. pag. 90.</note> All actions that man performeth unto man, are not parts of civil worſhip: but every act that man performeth directly or immediately to God, is a part of Divine worſhip, and ought meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to concern his glory: For it is impoſſible to conceive how the creature, who is infinite degrees inferiour to the Creator in excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and altogether unable to return the leaſt good back again to Him for the infinite bleſſings he hath received from him, ſhould perform any act immediately unto him but worſhip. A work commanded, is not large enough to comprehend the whole nature of worſhip, but doth diſtinguiſh true worſhip from falſe, as the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs of the heart doth ſincere worſhip from hypocritical and counterfeit. To ſay Man is a reaſonable creature alwayes enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſound health, is not the definition of Man, but of a ſound man; becauſe there be many ſubject to infirmities and diſeaſes, who yet be men: So to define Worſhip to be a work commanded of God, is to ſhew what lawful and holy Worſhip is,<note place="margin">Eſay 29.13. Matth. 15.9.</note> not what worſhip in general: For many things are worſhip which God never required. That Worſhip is true which God commandeth: that falſe, which man deviſeth: that ſincere that proceedeth from an honeſt heart, a good conſcience,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.34, 35.</note> and faith unfained: that hypocritical, which cometh from an halting, divided, double heart, or is performed by the outward man alone: But truth and ſincerity being ſpeciall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts of worſhip appointed and commanded of God, cannot come within the definition of worſhip in general. And as the means that God hath appointed to ſeal his promiſes or teach obedience, be acts of divine ſervice: So the means that man ſhall deviſe or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119318:21"/>of himſelf for that end and purpoſe, muſt needs be worſhip alſo. If God be worſhipped when obedience is taught by the preaching of the Goſpel, or his promiſes ſealed by the uſe of the Sacraments: When the ſame duty is taught by viſible ſigns, or the promiſe confirmed by new deviſed ſeals, he is worſhipped and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured: for every action whereby God is worſhipped, is worſhip; and every work whereby obedience is taught, is obedience or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. From hence it appears, that the definition of eſſential wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to be, [That which is neceſſarily required to God's ſervice, ſo as that the contrariety thereof muſt needs diſpleaſe him] is too ſhort, as that which agreeth not to all worſhip, but only to that which is true and ordained of God: For we know, many Traditions, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and Ceremonial obſervations are obtruded upon the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as worſhip, the contrary whereof would pleaſe, and not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God. Were not the precepts of men reprehended by the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> the Phariſaical waſhings taxed by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eſay 29.13. Matth. 15.9. Mar. 7.7. Col. 2.23.</note> and other Ceremonial obſervations condemned by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of worſhip, though falſe and erroneous? How could there be any will-worſhip, if all worſhip were neceſſarily required of God? Neither are thoſe Ceremonies only to be reputed eſſential parts of worſhip, that be urged with opinion of Sanctity, Neceſſity, Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, whether true or falſe: but thoſe ſigns alſo that are deviſed to be means of ſpiritual inſtruction by their notable and myſtical ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: It being a part and means of his worſhip, to teach his worſhip. To place the worſhip of God in Faith, Hope, and Love only, and not in external Rites and Ceremonies, is contrary to Truth and Reaſon: For then the Ceremonies of the Law, &amp; the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the New Teſtament muſt be reputed no parts of Gods eſſential worſhip, which is moſt abſurd.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calv.</hi> Inſt. l. 4. c. 10. Sect. 9.12.</note> The Papiſts are accuſed by the Learned of our ſide, to place the Worſhip of God in their vain Traditions and Obſervations. What worſhip do they in end, only acceſſary and accidental, as ſome call it? No, but eſſentiall and ſubſtantial: and yet they ſpeak of Rites and Ceremonies, which by the Canons and Conſtitutions of that Synagogue, are not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ained to be of abſolute neceſſity to ſalvation; as they plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and our Divines acknowledg: Whereby it is not hard to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what is meant by eſſential or ſubſtantial worſhip; that it ſtands not only in internal duties, but alſo in external Rite; and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which are acknowledged to be of no abſolute neceſſity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119318:22"/>
Now the better to conceive what warrant every part of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice muſt have from the Scripture, three things are to be diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in it.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the eſſential worſhip it ſelf, whether concerning mans duty, or the means of his Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, the natural Ceremonies, or voluntary compoſitions or geſtures of the body, as are with moderate deliberation uſed to ſhadow forth the hidden motions, affections, and diſpoſitions of the mind, that are begotten by the conſideration of Gods excellent Greameſs, Majeſty, Goodneſs, Love, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The third, is the circumſtances, and order of performance (which is by ſome called accidental, or acceſſary worſhip), ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern time, place, perſon, and manner of performance; all which are required in the celebration of Gods worſhip. Thus Divines make a difference (and that neceſſarily) betwixt the ſubſtance of worſhip, and the things annexed to it as neceſſary circumſtances. And as we muſt diſtinguiſh the ſubſtantial means of worſhip from the external teſtifications of inward devotion by natural Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; ſo muſt they be diſtinguiſhed from bare and naked circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of time, place, and manner of celebrating divine Myſteries: for circumſtances are meetly acceſſaries to worſhip, no parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if we ſpeak properly, according to the ordinary acceptation of the word,<note place="margin">1 King. 19.18. Hoſ. 13.2. Ezek. 18. 6.</note> in Claſſical Authors. But the geſtures of the body made, and purpoſely framed to ſhadow forth the hidden affection of the Soul, are external acts of adoration and worſhip. The true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of God are diſtinguiſhed from Idolaters by this, that they had not <hi>bowed the knee to Baal.</hi> Kiſſing, bowing to an Image, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as a ſervice of the Idol; and the whole worſhip of God is oft-times ſignified by the terms of kiſſing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.12. Eſay 45.23. Phil. 2.9, 10. Epheſ. 3.24. Joh. 4.20, 21. 1 Reg. 8.54. Ezr, 9.5. Deut. 4.19. Pſal. 95.5. Matth. 17.4. Matth. 2.1, 11.</note> bowing, kneeling, ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, falling down before him. In the old Teſtament, the worſhip of God is noted by this word, <hi>Carah,</hi> which ſignifieth the bending of the knees, or hams; <hi>Kadad,</hi> which ſignifieth to bow, or nod the head; <hi>Sagad,</hi> almoſt of the ſame ſignification; <hi>Schaphel, Schachah,</hi> and <hi>Shacack,</hi> which ſignify to bow the whole body, and ſometimes to fall flat upon the ground. In the New Teſtament, Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is noted by theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifieth to bow the knee; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is to worſhip by kiſſing, and caſting down himſelf at the knees of another. What? that to adore, is to give honour with the geſture of the body, aſwell as with the mind
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119318:22"/>or words: <hi>Priſcianus,</hi> and <hi>Nonnius,</hi> derive the word <hi>Adoratio</hi> of <hi>Ador,</hi> which ſignifieth fine flower, or corn whereof fine Cakes were made, which the <hi>Romans</hi> uſed in their Sacrifices. <hi>Valla</hi> derive it of <hi>oro,</hi> but yet he ſaith, <hi>Adorare nihilominus ſine ore ſieri,</hi> not, <hi>ſine flexu genuum ac geſtu corporis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It implyeth in it three acts; firſt, An apprehenſion of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of that which is adored.</p>
            <p>Secondly, An act of the Will, deſiring to do ſomething to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy our acknowledgment of this greatneſs, and our ſubjection and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriority.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, An outward act expreſſing the ſame.</p>
            <p>The two former are internal, the laſt is outward, bringing that to light that was hid in the heart; but the Hebrew, Greek, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine words, ſignifying adoration, do note an external humiliation, and either a proſtration of the whole body, or of ſome part, <hi>viz.</hi> the head, or the bending of the knee, or kiſſing of the hands, to ſhadow forth and expreſs the internal affection of the heart, which is the Soul and life of external worſhip. But if it be demanded what warrant theſe things muſt have from the Word of God, the anſwer is direct.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The actions of worſhip it ſelf, whatſoever are not preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and appointed of God, they are forbidden; for concerning them, nothing may be added, diminiſhed, or changed, but all things muſt be done according to Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Natural Ceremonies or Signes (as they are called),<note place="margin">Bell. de ſacr. l. 2. c. 29. ſect. ſecund. part. Quaedam ſunt ab ipſa natura, &amp;c.</note> which are but inward demonſtrations of the ſecret diſpoſition of the heart, are ſufficiently warranted by the light of Nature, and the Word of God, though they be not required as abſolutely neceſſary, nor particularly preſcribed, as be the ſubſtantial means of worſhip. And though no preciſe geſture be of abſolute neceſſity in any part of Gods worſhip; yet are theſe Ceremonies ſo far Divine,<note place="margin">Calv. Inſt. l. 4. c. 10. ſect. 30.</note> that it is not in the power of any Church in the World, altogether to prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Arbitrary Ceremonies concerning time, place, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of celebrating Divine Myſteries, are in the power of the Church, to be ordered as ſhe ſhall judg to be moſt convenient, and tending to edification; provided that all her Ordinances be ſquared accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the general rules of direction hid down in the Word of God, and nothing be done contrary to the integrity of Doctrine, the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119318:23"/>ſimplicity of Chriſtian Religion, the edification of the Church, good order, and the rules of love: and in all this, nothing is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but what is taught and maintained by Proteſtant Divines againſt the common Adverſaries of Gods Grace and truth; but ſigns ſignifying by proportion annexed to the ſolemn worſhip of God, are parts of his worſhip, not acceſſary, but ſubſtantial; proper, not accidental, in the ſenſe before explained.<note place="margin">Cont. Fauſt. l. 19. cap. 16. et Tract. in 10.80. et de Trin. l. 3. c. 4.</note> For Ceremonies ſignificant are viſible words (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calleth the Sacraments) teaching Doctrine true or falſe, as in ſignification they conſent or diſſent from the Word of God; and of neceſſity the Doctrine taught by Word, and Sign, muſt agree in one common nature. What is it to ſay the Sacraments are viſible words,<note place="margin">Urſin. tom. 2. ad Flac. Sect. reſp. pag. 1433.</note> but that they are Signes, Image<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Similitudes, Types, viſible Anti-types of the Word; or that the Sacraments as Signs, do repreſent that to the eyes, which words bring to the ears?</p>
            <p>Now the publick reading of Scripture for the edification of the Church, is acknowledged to be a part of Gods Worſhip; ſo is the Preaching,<note place="margin">Ut enim voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis oratio eſt cultus, quia eſt ſignum menta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis; ita adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio erit cultus, quia eſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num internae adorationis. Bell. de ſacr. l. 2. c. 3. prop. 5.</note> explaining, and applying of the Word; the text being the ſame for ſubſtance with the expoſition; And if to teach by word be a worſhip of God; to teach by ſign, whether ſignificative by the appointment of God, or declaratory by the invention of man, is worſhip alſo, when they teach one thing in uſe publick and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious.</p>
            <p>Again, all Actions whereby ſpirituall Duties are taught in Gods ſolemn Worſhip, are Acts whereby God is Worſhipped, and all Acts whereby God is Worſhipped in his ſolemn Servivce, is Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; as all Actions whereby he is obeyed, is Obedience. But ſignificant Ceremonies do teach ſpiritual Duties in the Worſhip of God; and conſequen ly God is Worſhipped by them, and they are Worſhip. Moreover, the Jewiſh Ceremonies Inſtituted by God, and Ceremonies ſignificative deviſed by Men, and annexed to the ſolemn Worſhip of God, do agree in the ſame common nature and uſe; both appropriated to the Worſhip of God, both outward ſhadows of myſtical ſignification to teach ſpirituall Duties: But the uſe of Jewiſh Ceremonies in the ſolemn Worſhip of God, was a part of his true and immediate Worſhip and Service: Therefore others alſo muſt be a part of his Worſhip; for agreeing with them in common nature and uſe, they muſt needs conſent in the common Nature of Worſhip, though they differ in their Adjuncts,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119318:23"/>true and falſe, as they diſſent in their ſpeciall Inſtitution; the one taking their Originall from God, the other ſpringing from Man's brain. The commandment of God, and the ſpeciall inſtituted ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of a Ceremony, makes it not barely to be Worſhip, but true and approved Worſhip; and the ſame thing practiſed to a like end, without Divine approbation, muſt needs be Worſhip, but falſe and erroneous: Incenſe offered to the true God according to his preſcription to an holy end, was an holy Sacrifice, pleaſing and acceptable; Incenſe offered to Saints without direction from God, is a Sacrifice alſo, becauſe both theſe are one in the common nature of a Sacrifice, but falſe and profane. Circumciſion, abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from Blood, and other legal Rites obſerved according to the preſcription of the Law, was an immediate Worſhip of God; but now to abſtain in like manner, and for the ſame end, is Superſtitious. Now, to take up the uſe of legall Rites, is Will-worſhip; becauſe they are not required at our hands: A thing in it ſelf indifferent, being commannded of God for ſome ſpeciall end and purpoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a neceſſary and immediate part of his Worſhip, though it was not ſo before; but if any man upon his own head ſhall uſe it to ſuch ends to which it is not appointed, or with the ſame opinion of holineſs and neceſſity; he ſtands guilty of deviſed Worſhip.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Martyr</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the popiſh Addition of Salt in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; ſaith, So then that which is added to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, is ſelf-worſhip; and no lawful and ſincere Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. <hi>Martyr. Com. pl. part.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.5. In Inſtitutions which are means to an end, the reſpect of the end is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo required to the end; but a right end not ſo.</note> It had been ſimply indifferent to offer a Lamb ſpeckled or unſpeckled in Sacrifice, had not the Lord determined they ſhould bring one without ſpot for an oblation; but if to the ſame end for which God ordained it ſhould be without ſpot, any man had preſumed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point or offer a Lamb without ſpot; in ſo doing, he had forged a Worſhip unto himſelf: This is no new piece of Doctrine, but what hath been acknowledged, and is maintained by our Divines againſt the Adverſaries. Laſtly, ſigns Sacramentall are parts of God's Worſhip: But ſignificant ſigns by analogy or propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are Sacramentall; as ſhall be ſhowed in the next Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="8">8. No ſigns Sacamentall are warrantable or lawfull, but what are Inſtituted of God, and approved in his Word; <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hereceived of the Lord, what he delivered to the Church of</hi> Corinth, <hi>touching the, Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.13. which muſt be underſtood of all other alſo: <hi>The Baptiſm of</hi> John, <hi>was it from Heaven or of Men?</hi> It was not from Men, but God: He is the Ordainer of all Sacraments, new or old; Our Divines maintain
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119318:24"/>againſt the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9.13, &amp; 17.19. <hi>Willet</hi> Con. 24. q. 4. Arg. 2. <hi>Divinum et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrum non eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet miſterium, ſi quicquam ex te adderes.</hi> Chryſ. homl. 7. in 1 Corrinth. <hi>Bell. de Sacr.</hi> l. 1. c. 9.14. &amp; de Script. l. 4. c. 5. <hi>Chriſtus in Eccleſia ſolus poteſt Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere.</hi> Mald. in Matth. 26.11. <hi>Zepper. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra. lib.</hi> 1. The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to move, lead, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct our dull and heavy hearts, by ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Creatures, that ſo our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in not hearing or marking the Word of God might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended. <hi>Jewel's</hi> Treatiſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> That the Sacraments are expreſly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of God in holy Scripture, and that in the Inſtitution of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there muſt be expreſs mention of the material parts thereof, as it was in the Inſtitution of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper; yea, the Papiſts themſelves acknowledge that Ceremonies Sacramental, muſt be Inſtituted by Authority, divine, not humane; though they refuſe to be judged in this by the Scripture, and fly to unwritten Traditions, which blaſphemouſly they make to be one part of the word of God, in authority equal to the holy Scripture: But ſigns appointed to ſignify by analogy or proportion, &amp; annexed to the ſolemn Worſhip of God, are Sacramental. The antients define a Sacrament to be, A viſible ſign or form of an inviſible Grace, A ſign not naturall, but voluntary; not indicant, but analogicall; teaching or ſhadowing by repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So they call a Sacrament, a viſible Word, as in Scripture they are termed Signs or Memorials. In modern Writers, the name Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is given to the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil; to the Altars, Sacrifices, Cherubins, Lights, and all Ceremonies or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for ſignification in time of the Law; as well as to the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, Manna, the Rock, the Red-Sea, Circumciſion, and the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal-Lamb: Some of which were inſtituted to teach Man his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as others to ſeal and confirm the Promiſe of God, or if all of them were ſeals of ſome ſpirituall Promiſes, they were all Signs of ſome ſpiritual Duty, and Sacramentall in both reſpects. Whence we may conclude, That the common nature of a Sacrament doth agree to ſigns determined by repreſentation to teach any duty that man oweth to God (his abſolute Soveraign, and mercifull Father in Chriſt Jeſus) whether Supernaturall or Morall. The Precepts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Book of Life, are, and do ſet forth the mind of God unto us, no leſſe than the Promiſes made therein; nor can any reaſon be given, why the repreſentation of ſome ſpirituall Duty [for all Duties that man is to perform unto God in Chriſt are ſpirituall Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,] by a myſtical Rite, ſhould not as properly pertain to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Sacrament; as the ſhadowing or ſealing of ſome ſpirituall Promiſe.<note place="margin">Quanquam ne profeſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem fidei. Nam attendendum non tantum quid velit qui profitetu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiam quid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ptum ſit ei, apud quem opertet profeſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ch. de Sacr. lib. 1. cap. 8.</hi> urſin. <hi>tom. 2. pag. 1630.</hi>
               </note> What the Word doth bring to the ear, that the Sacrament
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119318:24"/>doth exhibit to the other ſenſes: The whole Scripture doth teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, That from the beginning of the World, the Lord did intend this in Inſtituting Ceremonies, that they ſhould repreſent thoſe things to the Eyes of men, which his heavenly Word doth offer to their Ears. But commandments are part of the Word as well as Promiſes; The Will of God manifeſting what he will do for us, is a myſtery; ſo is it preſcribing what Service he will have from us, and a viſible, corporal, material element determined to teach either of them, or both, is a ſign Sacramentall and myſticall, expreſſing ſome ſacred myſtery to the Eye, <note>plac="marg" Signa cum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res divinas ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibentur Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta vocan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Aug. de Doctr. Chr. lib. 3. cap. 6.</hi> &amp; ad <hi>Max. Ep. 5.</hi>
               </note> as the Word doth to the ſenſe which receiveth the Voyce. We know no more what Service God will have a Chriſtian perform unto his Highneſſe, then we do what good he would have men to expect from him by a lively Faith; and it ſeems altogether as lawfull for man to deviſe ſigns for the confirmation of his Faith, as to admoniſh and teach his Duty. What difference can be made betwixt an addition to the means of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction appointed of God, and to the means of our aſſurance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by him: The commandments and the Promiſes are ſo knit together, that it cannot be conceived how a ſign ſhould be appointed to teach man his Duty, and not to aſſure him of ſome good from God in the uſe thereof: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Will is made known by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, wherein he freely bin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>elf to bleſs us upon condition of ſincere and faithfull Obedie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s he obligeth us to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to his Commandments that we may be bleſſed; and the ſigns added to the Word do teach both, as in the Word it ſelf both parts are publiſhed. Again, it is one proper end of the Sacraments by ſtriking the ſenſes by outward repreſentative Elements to teach the underſtanding, help the memory, ſtirr up the affections, and excite devotion: But for this end alſo are ſignificant Rites deviſed, unleſs we ſhall confeſſe them to be vain, idle, fruitleſs, abſurd and ſenſleſs; And thus agreeing with Sacraments in their nature and end; of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity they muſt be confeſſed to be Ceremonies Sacramental: The Scripture doth not ſo diſtinguiſh betwixt Signs &amp; Seals, or ſigns ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificative &amp; obſignant; as to make the one Sacramental, not the other: rather under the name ſign it expreſſeth the nature of a Sacrament, which conſiſteth in the analogy &amp; proportion which is betwixt a ſign determined to ſignify, and the thing ſignified. The ſigns which it hath pleaſed God to add to his Covenant, are not bare, naked, empty ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, but lively Seals of divine Grace Promiſed, &amp; effectual Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of man's duty; ſigns of man's duty, Signs and Seals both of God's
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119318:25"/>ſpeciall favour and mercy in Chriſt Jeſus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>urſia.</hi> Catech. q. 65. explic. 1. Gen. 9.12. By the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment man is bound to God; and by the ſame, God vouchſafeth to bind himſelf to man <hi>Jewel's</hi> Treatiſe of the Sacrament. See 1 Cor. 9.2. 2 Tim. 2.19. Apo. 7.2, &amp; 9, 4 Matth 27.66. <hi>Viſ. Urſie.</hi> tom. 4. pag. 1614. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1668. <hi>Urſin.</hi> pag. 1673.</note> and in both reſpects Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments: Some ſigns are ordained meerly to aſſure and confirm unto us the Promiſes which God hath been pleaſed to make; Some both to teach viſibly what the Lord requireth and commandeth in his holy Truth, and to confirm our Faith in what he hath promiſed in his holy Word; but all are Sacraments in each reſpect, and what is a Seal, but a viſible ſign annexed to a Promiſe to teſtify or aſſure it: And how can a ſign be added to it but, it muſt teſtify or confirm? Even from hence that it is ſet to the Promiſe by him who hath Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to make it, and Power to make it good, it is a Seal: So that the Word <hi>Seal</hi> doth rather note the ſpeciall nature and end of ſome Signs as they are referred to the Promiſes ratified &amp; aſſured by them, than expreſs the common nature of a Sacrament. In orthodox Writers a Sign of God's Promiſe, and a Seal of his Will and Pleaſure; are put for one and the ſame: And whether we look to the truth of the thing it ſelf, or the Arguments which are brought to prove the lawfulneſs of deviſing ſymbolicall and analogicall Signs; we ſhall find it as lawfull to deviſe Signs obſignant of God's Promiſes, as ſignificative of his pleaſure and man's duty: For to be a Teacher of the Underſtanding, and Exciter of Devotion, requireth power ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall, no leſs than to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>firmer of the heart; and he that hath Authority to ordain means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>mal for any of theſe ends, can bleſſe them for all; he that ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> appoint them for any one, can do it ſo none, they being all ſupernaturall; exceeding the power of any Creature: Man hath as much power to ſeal what he cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, as to teach by his own Sign, that which he cannot bleſſe to that end. The Inſtitution of means ſerving for the ſpirituall Inſtruction of the Church, pertaineth to him that bleſſeth them; to him it belongeth to ordain Seals of his Promiſes, that can confert the Grace promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and both theſe are peculiar to one alone, the Lord of All. The arguments that are alledged to demonſtrate the liberty of the Church, to Inſtitute and deviſe ſignificant Ceremonies, do ſpeak for power to ordain Signs obſignant, if they conclude any thing at all. <hi>Solomon</hi> [they ſay] built a brazen Altar, and ſet it beſides the Altar of the Lord, offering thereon burnt Offerings:<note place="margin">2 King. 18.22. Apo. 6.9. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 13.10. Matth. 23.19. with Job. 17.17 Exod. 24.4.</note> Here is a humane Invention, a new Ceremony, having neceſſary relation to Worſhip in Sacrificing: And was not the Altar, appointed for Burnt-offering, an eſſentiall part of God's Worſhip in time of the Law? was it not a Type and Sign obſignant of Chriſt and his Grace? was not this Altar erected
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119318:25"/>by <hi>Solomon</hi> for the ſame principall and ſpeciall end and uſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jun.</hi> Innor. <hi>in</hi> Exod 24.4. <hi>Par.</hi> in Gen. 12.7. <hi>Mart.</hi> loc. com. <hi>part.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. Sect. 21. <hi>Polan.</hi> Synt. tom. 2. lib. 9 <hi>cap</hi> 36. <hi>Fulk</hi> againſt <hi>Rhem</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.19.8.7. <hi>Biza</hi> Epiſt. 8. Zepper. <hi>de Saer.</hi> l. 2. <hi>Maldon.</hi> in Jo. 20. <hi>Rhem.</hi> in 1 Tim. 4.14.18. <hi>Martyr</hi> thus reaſoach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water; It is not the condition of men to inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at their own pleaſure, becauſe that is proper to God alone, and to none beſides him; for Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Mart loc. com.</hi> p. 4. c. 9. <hi>Juni.</hi> Annot. <hi>in</hi> Exod, 25. <hi>Aſſunſta ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>atem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run figuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt coaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pta, non propter ſiguram rerum ſed prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Naturam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurarum.</hi>
               </note> for which God hath ordained the Brazen Altar to be erected? An Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar was a principal Inſtrument of divine Service (ſaith <hi>Martyr</hi>). The Altar in the Temple was a figure of Chriſt's only ſingular true Sacrifice once offered, and never can be ſacrificed again, ſaith <hi>Fulk</hi> our of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if the Church, in the time of the Goſpel, may take upon her to deviſe new ſignificant Signs in God's Worſhip, from this Example of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and that ſuch as be in kind different from them that are inſtituted of him; She may challenge Power to ordain Signs, to ordain obſignant Sign; of Chriſt, and his Grace, eſſentiall parts of God's immediate Worſhip, and in their proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ends, one with Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper; as that Altar ſerved to the ſame purpoſe that the other did, which was builded by the expreſs Commandment of the Lord. Again, it is very uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al with Writers, proteſtant and Popiſh, to call external Ceremonies ſignifying holy things, by the name of Sacraments, Sacramentalls, or Sacramental Actions.</p>
            <p>It is objected, If ſignification be a principall part of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then all the Moral Signs uſed in the Levitical Worſhip; as namely, Bells, Lavers, Lights, Candleſticks, and other Ceremonial Inſtruments, even unto the very Snuffers of the Tabernacle, ſhould (things taking their denomination from the principal parts) be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly deemed Sacraments: And the like may be ſaid of Hog's Fleſh, from touching the Corps of the dead, from Linſey-wolſey Apparel, and a hundred ſuch others, whereby diverſe Moralities are ſignified, but no Sacrament implied; but this nothing infringeth the ſtrength of the former Reaſons. For the Cerenionies of the Law were either taken to figure out the Truth of things, or co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for the Nature of the Figures, not for the Figure of things; which were onely annexed to the Figures, but of themſelves did not figure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> point out any ſpiritual things: Of this ſort were many things pertaining to the Tabernacle, Ark, Altars, and Sacrifices; which did not by themſelves typify any thing, but onely pertain to the material conſtitution of the Type: And amongſt them are the Snuffers and Tongs of the Tabernacle to be reckoned; for it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhewed that of themſelves they were ordained to repreſent any myſtical Promine or ſpiritual Duty, but did onely belong as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Ornaments to the Service of the Tabernacle. Therefore
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119318:26"/>we may exclude them from the number of Sacraments, and yet hold the common Nature of a Sacrament to conſiſt in proportion betwixt the Sign determined to ſignify, and the thing ſignified. Secondly, amongſt the Signs here degraded, as unworthy the Name, and not participating in the Nature of the Sacraments; ſuch are mentioned as did ſeal and aſſure ſpiritual promiſes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.105. Prov. 6.21. 2 Pet. 1.19. Rev. 4.5.</note> and not barely teach or ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify moral duties; The Gandleſticks and Lights, did they not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the light of the Divine Word, and Holy Scripture, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God's holy Spirit enlightning the Church of God? The waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Law, did not they ſeal the purging away of Sin by the Blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.22. Pſal. 26.6.</note> and that we being ſprinkled in our hearts from an evil Conſcience, and waſhed in our bodies with pure water, might draw near with a true heart, in full aſſurance of Faith? The High-Prieſt was a Type of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Exod. 28.2.</note> our Mediator, and the Bells of Gold that were placed upon the Ephod did ſhaddow forth the Voice of Chriſt, which was to be heard of the People in his Teaching and Inſtruction. Wherefore, if a Sacrament be a Sign of God's Grace or free Promiſe, the Lavers, Lights, Bels, Candleſticks uſed in the Levitical Worſhip may truly be called Sacraments:<note place="margin">Heb. 9.2.</note> And by Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.5. &amp; 9.24.</note> calling things that pertained to the Service of the Tabernacle, <hi>Examples, Shadows, and Figures of heavenly things;</hi> worthy Divines have not ſpared to call them Sacraments: Thus writeth <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Catech. rud. <hi>c. 20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ideo multis Sacramentis viſibilibus onerati ſunt, quo ſervili jugò premerentur in obſervationibus ciborum, &amp; in Sacrificiis ammalium, &amp; in ali is innumer abilibus, quae tamen ſigna erant rerum ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualium ad Dominum Jeſum Chriſtum, &amp; ad Eccleſiam pertinentium.</hi> Thirdly, we find the Name Sacrament given to thoſe Signs pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Levitical Worſhip, which of all others (if in truth that Title may be given unto any) might moſt properly be called Moral, by ſignification of Man's ſpiritual Duty and Obedience: The Shew-Bread,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.30. &amp; 39.36. 1 Chron. 9.32. &amp; 23.29.</note> called in Hebrew, <hi>Bread of faces,</hi> or of <hi>preſence;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Loavs or Cakes were to be ſet before the Face or in the Preſence of God continually; and, the Bread of ordering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, becauſe they were diſpoſed in certain order and time: In Greek,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.4. Mar. 2.26. Heb. 9.2.</note> the Bread of Propoſition; and, in a contrary order, The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Bread or Cakes; Did it not ſignify the Office of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they ſhould ſtand continually before God, receive his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and ſanctify themſelves to his Obedience: As the Ark ſignified the preſence of God in his Church, ſo his Table with the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119318:26"/>twelve Cakes, ſignified the Multitude of the faithful preſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God in his Church, continually ſerving him; It may be, this placing of the Shew-bread before the Ark might ſignify, that the Lord hath his Church continually in his ſight, and doth take care thereof: But the principal thing taught thereby was, the ſincerity and purity of them that walk in the Light, and preſent themſelves before God: What duty ſoever Man oweth to God, it is to be performed by vertue of the Coveuant that he hath made with Man; and ſo the Signs of God's Promiſe do imply Man's Duty, and the Signs of Man's Duty do imply God's Promiſe, though ſome do ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the one; ſome, the other. And from this we learn,<note place="margin">Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſibilia ſigna, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus doctrina illa declaratur &amp; obſignatur. <hi>Mart.</hi> de Sacr. <hi>l. 1. c. 2. q. 8.</hi>
               </note> what is a Sacrament in general, <hi>viz.</hi> A Sign Analogical of God's Will and Pleaſure; whether teaching what he requires, or repreſenting and fealing what he promiſeth: True Sacraments are Signs and Seals inſtituted of God to ſignify his Will, and confirm his' Promiſes: But divine Inſtitution is to be removed from the definition of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in general, as that which doth diſtinguiſh true from falſe, and not explicate the common nature of the thing.</p>
            <p>The diſtinction that ſome make of Signs moral, ſignifying the ſpiritual Obedience which Man oweth unto God, and myſtical or ſacramental, repreſenting and confirming the Promiſes of God, is not to be received: For Signs teaching to the Eye by repreſentation, what the Word bringeth to the Ear, are Sacraments ſignifying the ſame thing that the Word doth, as hath been ſhewed before. But Signs analogical muſt be diſtinguiſhed from negative Precepts, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the uſe of this or that in it ſelf indifferent. Jewiſhabſtinence from diverſe Mears legally unclean, to ſhew that they were ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from other Nations, to be a peculiar People unto the Lord, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not properly be called a Sign ſignifying by reſemblance; For God in that Law ſeemeth not ſo much to reſpect the Nature of thoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creatures prohibited to be eaten;<note place="margin">Act. 1.15, 16, 17, 28. <hi>Juni.</hi> Annot. in Lev. 11.</note> but by this external Sign he would have his People to be diſcerned and ſeparated from all other People. And if this figurative commanded Abſtinence ſhould be deemed ſacramental, what errour is therein committed? As by ſuch Abſtinence the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> profeſſed themſelvs to be the peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, ſeparated from all idolatrous Nations round about them; ſo did the Lord by this Commandment ſignify and aſſute, that he had taken them to Covenant, and made choice of them to be his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119318:27"/>Treaſure. The reaſon whereby this commanded Abſtinence is urged, doth confirm thus much,<note place="margin">Lev. 11.44.</note> 
               <hi>I am the Lord your God, ye ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſanctify your ſelvs, and ye ſhall be holy, for I am holy; neither ſhall ye defile your ſelves with any manner of creeping thing that creepeth upon the Earth: For I am the Lord that brought you up out of the Land of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt to be your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe figurative Ordinances then were Signs of the Covenant, teaching what duty man owed to God, and aſſuring back again what favour they had with God: And when the Apoſtle, ſpeaking of Levitical Service,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.9, 10.</note> which ſtood onely in Meats, and Drinks, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe waſhings, and carnal Ordinances, impoſed on them until the time of Reformation,<note place="margin">Beza <hi>in Heb.</hi> 9.10.</note> calleth them figures for the time then preſent; doth he not in effect ſay they were Sacraments? The Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evill, is called a Sacrament, or a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Precept,<note place="margin">K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cherm. <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol.</hi> lib <hi>2. c 2.</hi> Polan. <hi>Synt.</hi> lib. 6. cap. <hi>44. Chaimer. pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat. tom. 4. lib. 1. cap. 7.</hi> Si ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> propter ſe, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex ſuanatura, certe &amp; propter aliud &amp; ex In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slitutione.</note> by many excellent and worthy Divines, as it did ſignify to Man, that he ſhould have experience of good, ſo long as he continued in Obedience, and of evil or miſery if he did diſobey; and as it was a Sign whereby he was admoniſhed of his mutability, and tried in his Obedience: But if forbearance of the Tree of Knowledge was an Act Sacramental, much more Abſtinence from ſuch Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts as by the Law were forbidden unto the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Nor ſhall we need to fear the force of the Jeſuite, inſulting over Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants by this Objection; <hi>viz.</hi> If Sacraments be onely Signs, then the Cruciſix is a better Sign to ſignify the death of Chriſt than the Sacraments. For we acknowledge our Sacraments not bare Signs of God's Promiſe, or ſignifications of Man's Duty; but holy Seals of what he promiſeth to us, and we by ſtipulation promiſe back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain unto him. And this the Jeſuite himſelf doth and cannot but acknowledge, howſoever impudently againſt Conſcience he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes unto us his own device for our Doctrine: But we may further tell this Romiſh Proctor, that a Crucifix made to teach by propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or reſemblance, that Chriſt dyed for our ſins, or that God gave his Son to ſuffer death for our Redemption, is a Sacrament, or a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Sign, ſignifying by ſpecial Repreſentation, though falſe and erroneous, becauſe it is deviſed by man, not ordained by God: The greateſt Defenders of myſtical Signs, diſtinguiſh them into mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and ſacramental; which differ (ſay they) from the former, both as the Sacramental are ſignificant by ſpecial Repreſentation, and as they are obſignant by ratifying and applying of God's Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119318:27"/>of Grace unto us: And from this we may gather, that Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſigus, which ſignify, by repreſentation, the promiſe of God (as the Crucifix doth) are Sacramental, elſe is the diſtinction it ſelf faulty, and the difference which is made betwixt ſigns Moral, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental. And yet we make not Signification the principal part of thoſe ſpecial Sacraments of the Old or New Teſtament, which it pleaſed God to add to his gratious and free Covenant; but Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſignification is ſo proper to the Sacraments, that whatſoever ſign is ordained to ſignify and repreſent any ſuch promiſe, it is thereby made a Sacrament. The Cherubims in the Law, are called Types, and Sacraments of thoſe times; in all reaſon, the Crucifix is in that ſenſe to be deemed a Sacrament of theſe times; but vain and falſe, becauſe it is deſtitute of Divine approbation. And what advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage hath the Jeſuite gotten by this wiſe diſpute? he hath notably diſcovered their impudent boldneſs, in preferring their own ſinfull devices, before the ſacred O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>nances of God; and their notorious preſumption in attempring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which they cannot but acknowledg to be proper to the Lord alone.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Experience teſtifieth, that ſigns ſignificant deviſed by men, have been the ſeeds, ſparkles, and inſtruments of divers errors,<note place="margin">Whitak. de Sc. q. 6. c. 14. arg. ult. Calv. opuſc. de Neceſſ. refor. pag. 59.60.</note> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, and Idolatries; but they never did, or ſhall do, good in the Church of God. The bravery and exceſs that is ſeen in Popiſh Temples, doth affect, move, and draw the eye, but is of no worth to true Piety, devotion, and motions of mind, pleaſing to God. It hath been ſhewed before, and is further to be proved afterward, that no true Piety or ſincere devotion of mind can be ſtirred up in us by humane Traditions.</p>
            <p n="10">10. And leſt this truth confirmed by ſo many Arguments out of the Word of God, ſhould yet be caſt off upon ſuſpition of novelty, or not relliſh ſavourly to ſome palats for want of the ſauce of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authority; It ſhall not be amiſs to produce the teſtimonies of worthy Divines, to ſhew what hath been their Judgment in this point. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nulla doctrina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Matth. 21.25. viſ. Calv. reſp. ad verſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. opuſc. pag. 413. In Tim. 4.14. SS. 18.</note> 
               <hi>nullum ſacrum ſignum debet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pios admitti, niſi à Deo profecta eſſe conſtet; nec eſt in hominum arb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin, quicquam excudere. Fulk</hi> againſt the <hi>Rhemiſts,</hi> 
               <q>The true Church of Chriſt ſubmitteth her ſelf to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles in all things, and is content with thoſe Ceremonies which Chriſt and his Apoſtles by his Commandment have left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us.</q> Dr. <hi>Raynolds</hi> ſpeaking of Popiſh ſignificant Rites, hath
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119318:28"/>theſe words,<note place="margin">Cenſur. Apoc. tom. 2. prael. 243.</note> 
               <hi>Simplicius multo veteres, quanquam et ipſi nimium pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſmodi myſteriis excogitandis, ut omnes propemodum ritus in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta converterent; non quin poſſint omnia, quae uſpiam oculis uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pamus, merito ſuggerere nobis anſam earum rerum meditandarum qua faciunt ad pietatem; ſed, quod magna religione cavendum eſt in eccleſia, ne convertamus in morem Sacramentorum interpretationibus hujuſmodi, ut permiſceamus inſtituta humana cum inſtitutis ipſius Chriſti, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ita ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum authoritatem communiamus commentis hominum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Heb. 8.5.</note> Paraeus ſaith, <hi>Quicquid etiam Sacramentis divinis ornatus, vel perfectionis, vel ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficationis auguſtioris gratia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffingitur, qualia ſexcenta circa Baptiſmun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> et Euchariſtiam habet papatus, exorciſmos, ſal, ſputum, chriſma, &amp;c. id totum tanquam inane et evanidum oraculo hoc improbatur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Synopſis in 12. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. q. 8. Non poteſt ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les homo inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuere Caeremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am, adquam ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>queretur gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Sp. Sancti. Bell. de Sac. l. 2. cap. 24.</note> Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> ſpeaking of the Ceremonies and Rites of Baptiſm, ſaith, <q>It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the rule of the Goſpel, that there ſhould be ſuch types, ſhadows, ſignifications, brought into the ſervice of God, as the Papiſts make in Baptiſm; for ſeeing we have the body which is Chriſt, all ſuch ſhadows ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> boliſhed; In one Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they (<hi>ſc,</hi> the Papiſts) have forged and found out many, as their Chriſm,</q> Oyl, Salt, Spittle, &amp;c. None of thoſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were uſed when Chriſt himſelf was Baptized; which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding had been moſt fit, conſidering the worthineſs of his perſon, which was Baptized; neither did Chriſt give any ſuch thing in charge to his Diſciples, but biddeth them onely Preach and Baptize <hi>In the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Nor yet were any ſuch Ceremonies in uſe in the Apoſtles times.<note place="margin">Act. 10.4.</note> St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Can any man forbid Water, that theſe ſhould not be Baptized.</hi> He calleth not for Oyl, Salt, Spittle, or any ſuch thing, but Water onely. And a little after he produceth the witneſs of two Martyrs againſt theſe Ceremonie.<note place="margin">Act. and Men. Hauk. 1. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. Ann. 1555.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas Hauks,</hi> 
               <q>I deny (ſaith he) in Baptiſm all things invented by man, as your Oyl, Cream, Salt, Spittle, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uring of Water.</q>
               <hi>John Denly,</hi> holy Martyr. The <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch</hi> ſaid to <hi>Philip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. and Mon. Denl. anſw. to art. 6. Anno. 1555. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſti. l. 4. c. 10. ſect. 23.</note> 
               <hi>See here is Water.</hi> We do not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead, he asked for any Cream, Oyl, Spit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, Conjured Water; for it ſeemeth that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> had Preached no ſuch thing unto him. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Unde colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus, partem reverentiae quae illi defertur, in eo eſſe poſitam, dum in eo colendo ſimpliciter quod mandat, nullas noſtras miſcendo inventiones ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quimur.</hi> That he ſpeaketh of deviſed ſymbolical ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gns, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the inſtances he giveth in that, and the two Sections follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oc com. p. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. ſect. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Martyr,</hi> 
               <q>Seeing God is altogether the wiſeſt, he hath no
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119318:28"/>need that we ſhould by our imagination, or endeavour, prepare Inſtruments for him. And afterwards in the ſame Chapter;<note place="margin">Sect. 16.</note> Neither can they eaſily eſcape, which imbrace exorciſms, but that of one Sacrament they make many, ſeeing they make ſo many Signs, which they will have to be accounted holy; adding Oyl, Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, Exſufflations, and ſuch like.</q> So as one Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm doth degenerate into many. Neither muſt they be heard, when, to the intent to mock the ſimple, they feign a difference between Sacraments and Sacramentalls, which is altogether ſophiſtical; for diſtinctions are to be received gladly, but thoſe to be ſuch as are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our of the very nature of the things, becauſe they bring much light to Controverſies; but thoſe diſtinctions which ſpring out of the brain of Sophiſters, onely for the ſhifting off of Arguments, are altogether to be refuſed.<note place="margin">Conſeſ. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb. tit. de Caerem. Eccl.</note> The Judgment of the Church of <hi>Wittem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> is thus ſet down in the Harmony of Confeſſions, <hi>Nec licet vel veteres ritus legis reſtaurare, vel novos comminiſci ad adumbrandam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem Evangelio jam patefactam et illuſtratam: quales ſunt, interdiu accendere cereos, ad ſignificandam lucem Evangelii; aut uti vexillis cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus, ad ſignificandam victoriam Chriſti per crucem; quod genus eſt univerſa panoplia veſtium Miſſalium, quam aiunt adumbrare totan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; et multa id genus alia. Multo minus licet inſtituere Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonias aut ſacra, quorum meritis expientur peccata, et accipiatur reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um coelorum: Nam de priori illo genere Caeremoniarum et Sacrorum, Chriſtus ex Eſaia concionatur; Fruſtra, inquiens, colunt me, docentes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrimas, pracepta hominum: et Paulus, Nequis vos judicet in cibo aut po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, aut in parte diei feſti, &amp;c.</hi> The Church of <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 17. ad Confeſſ. Sax. Obſ. 1. Tom. 4. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bapt. lib. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cap. 16. ſect. 27. Annot. maj. in Jo. 4.23.</note> in their obſervations upon the Confeſſion of the Church of <hi>Saxony,</hi> write thus, <hi>Ac perinde ne myſticos quidem ullos, alioqui non impios; ut qui,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sed in hoc capite</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cham.</hi> ſpeaking of Popiſh Rites in Baptiſm) <hi>merito damnamus, qui ea addiderunt, quibus myſteria af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finxerint, prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſignificationes; et quidem eorum affectuun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> qui per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent ad aquam Baptiſmi, &amp;c.</hi> The Judgment of <hi>Bezd</hi> is well known, and more than once uttered by himſelf; <hi>Sacramentis</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>pront divinitus ſunt ab unico noſtro legiſtatore ordinata, quicquam vel detrahere, ac multo magis novas figuras vel umbras ullas in Eccleſiam invehere, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efariam eſſe audaciam, ex verbo Dei omnes</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>tam expreſſe damnantis, et ignem externum olim altari ſuo inferre prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentis, affirmanus. Haec noſtra eſt de Spirituali cultu divino ſententia, his Chriſti verbis conſenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a; niſi forte ſublatas, licet divinitus inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119318:29"/>Moſaicas figuras et umbras arbitramur, ut alia ab hominibus il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum loco ſubſtituerentur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De cult. Sacr. l. 3. c. 7. n. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Junius</hi> aſſenteth unto the former; <hi>Quod ſi ad uſum inſtituere non poteſt quiſquam, profecto ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad ſignificatiorem homo legitime poteſt adhibere, niſi humano et irrogante inſtituto, ne in priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to quidem, quanto minus in Eccleſia Dei et publica adminiſtratione ipſius. Danaeus</hi> is of the ſame mind.<note place="margin">Cont. Bell. de cult. Sac. l. 3. cap. 7.</note> It is Blaſphemy to think that any outward thing may be made a Sign in the Church, unleſs it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ordained in the Word, and commanded by God himſelf to be uſed unto that end.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. l. 3. cap. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Junius</hi> again profeſſeth his Judgment in this matter; <hi>Res autem alias, ac non neceſſarias, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ordini convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſi volet quiſquam inſtituere; eum non pervicaciter velimus oppugnare, ſed tria tamen cum animo ſuo expendat cupimus. Primum qua authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te exemplove adductus, ſanctam Dei Eccleſiam et ſimplicitatem myſterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Chriſti (Cujus ſolius vocem agnoſcunt et ſequuntur oves, quia ſolum audiri mandavit pater</hi> Jo. 10.27.) <hi>circumveſtiendam eſſe puter humanis traditionibus quas repudiat Chriſtus. Secundum, quem ad finem res ſuas adſui divinis judicet oportere: nan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſi ut cum alii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conformetur, aequius foret alias Eccleſias tis conformari quae verbum Dei accedum proxime ex conſilio Cypriani, quam has ſe illis adjungere; ſi ut h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ora ſint omnia, quid ſimplicitate Chriſti honeſtius, quid honeſtate ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us? ſi voluntatem, Eſto ſane: at illud Tertulliani cogitandum, Volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Dei eſſe neceſſitatem ſummam, nec Dei Eccleſiam in divinis rebus vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatibus humanis obligari. Tertium, quis tandem eventus ex huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis traditionibus conſequatur, ut diuturna oſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dit experientia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="arguments">
            <div type="argument">
               <head>Of the <hi>Surplice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Attire or veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be diſtinguiſhed into ſour ſorts.</note>THere is a fourfold diſtinction of Attire. 1. Natural. 2. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. 3. Eccleſiaſtical by Divine inſtitution. 4. Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal by humane ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ointment.</p>
               <p>The Natural is ſuch, by which the difference of Sexes, of Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and Female is profeſſed;<note place="margin">Calv. harm. in lib. Moſ. expoſ. 7. Precept. and others. Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of Stage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playes, pag. 10.</note> this is Moral and perpetuall, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.5.</p>
               <p>The Civil is, when for eaſe, ſpeedier diſpatch of ſome civil bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, ornament, or politick differencing of degree in Office, Age, Trade, &amp;c. diverſity of habit is uſed; and this is Arbitrary, and lawfull, ſo that the rules of modeſty be obſerved. <hi>Whitgift def. of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119318:29"/>anſw. to adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. tract.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 264. <hi>Hooker Eccleſiaſt. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>S.</hi> 78. <hi>pag.</hi> 424.</p>
               <p>Thoſe are Eccleſiaſtical by Divine Inſtitution which the Lord, and Law-giver of his Church ordained to be uſed by Prieſts and Levites in the ſolemn worſhip of God,<note place="margin">Exod. 28, 12.29, 30, 40, 41, 43.</note> and in the place of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: theſe veſtiments continued neceſſary in uſe, untill the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Levitical Rites, and then determined.</p>
               <p>Such are Eccleſiaſticall by humane inſtitution, as man of his own head hath appropriated to Religious worſhip, or ſolemn Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical uſe. Of this ſort and kind I take the Surplice to be, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do make queſtion of the lawfulneſs thereof. My argument againſt it. I diſpoſe in this form.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Argum."/> All Veſtments appropriated to the ſolemn Worſhip of God, and appointed for ſignification of ſpiritual Duties by the Will of Man, without Warrant out of the Word of God, are unlawful.</p>
               <p>But the Surplice is a Veſtment appropriated to the ſolemn. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and appointed for the ſignification of ſpiritual Duties, by the Will of Man, without Warrant out of the Word of God. Therefore it is unlawful.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Propoſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſix Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note>The truth of the Propoſition may be cleared by theſe Reaſons fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All ſuch Veſtments as the Propoſition ſpeaketh of, are an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal form of Worſhip; both becauſe that in their common nature or kind, they agree with the Levitical Veſtments, which I ſuppoſe will not be denyed to have been parts of their external Worſhip, as well as other Rites among them. Homil. <hi>againſt perill of Idolatry, part.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 55. ſaith, All outward Jewiſh Rites wherewith God was honoured in the Temple, were <hi>Cultus.</hi> For what good definition can be given of Worſhip, which may not be predicated and affirmed of thoſe Rites? To be inſtituted of God, or of Man, doth not vary the common nature of Worſhip, but diſtinguiſh it into true and falſe, in which Adjuncts the common nature of Worſhip doth not conſiſt. Alſo, would not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arments of myſtical ſignification ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to ſolemn Worſhip, be Jewiſh in ſpecial, not in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon nature onely, if the Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> High ſhould Authorize them? And if they be Worſhip, and deviſed by Man, then they are Will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which God condemneth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If this <hi>Major</hi> be not true, what ſhould hinder, but that man may bring many of the Ceremonies of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> into the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119318:30"/>Church of the new Teſtament; for if one Jewiſh Rite may be brought in, why not any. It need not be doubted, but that Veſtments meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Eccleſiaſtical and Myſtical, are Jewiſh, though not in number, (or perhaps in ſome other petty differences), yet in kind: and are they not then the ſame? <hi>Luke</hi> 14.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.9. Dr. <hi>Raynolds</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. with <hi>Hart.</hi> cap. 8. diviſ. 4. pag. 494, 495.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Either Veſtments meerly Eccleſiaſticall and Myſtical, inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Man,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.9. &amp; 39, 40, 42, 43, &amp; 27, 19. 1 Chro. 28.12. 2 Chro. 29.5.</note> are unlawful; or elſe it had been lawful for the Jewiſh Church to have deviſed to themſelves, and uſed, thoſe Prieſtly Robes that were in uſe among them, though God had not appointed them; or they might have invented others of the ſame kind afterwards, and have added to thoſe God appointed: but this they might not do. It's true, that this would increaſe the multitude of Ceremonies, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Ceremonies of one ſort, would make them<note n="(f)" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> proteſt. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal. Lib. 1. Cap. 3. Sect. 3.</note> inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, becauſe this carryeth with it change of circumſtances, whereon conveniency or inconveniency doth depend. But if one Ceremony be lawful, hundreds of the ſame kind be lawful alſo; for the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one is predicated of all of that ſort. It cannot be truly ſaid, That the Jewiſh Church had leſs liberty to deviſe Eccleſiaſtical Rites (whatſoever ſome ſay),<note n="(g)" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sparks</hi> Perſwaſions to uniformity. cap. 3.8, 5. pag. 11. Joſh. 22.10.</note> than the Chriſtian Church hath; except the Chriſtian Church could under the Lord's Charter ſhew this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to be granted unto her. Add further, that the ſpeciall Ground that the maintainers of Ceremonies do or can bring in, for the now-urged Ceremonies, is the fact of the <hi>Reubenites</hi> building the Altar. If this Argument be of any force, muſt they not grant liberty to the Church of the Jews, as well as the Church of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Therefore, if men deny the Jews that liberty which the Chriſtian Church may rightfully claim, they will prove themſelves to ſtand upon no Ground.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Such Veſtiments cannot be uſed in Faith, without which the uſe thereof is ſinful. Faith, in this place, is a firm aſſurance of mind and conſcience,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.23.</note> reſting on aſſured Ground, that the thing which a man doth, is allowed of God to be done by him: So that two things are here implyed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Act to be done,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin.</hi> in loc. &amp; others. Vid. <hi>Marlo.</hi> in loc.</note> be allowed of God; otherwiſe the conſcience that doth it, how confident ſoever it be, is erroneous and faulty.<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Covel</hi>'s anſ. to Mr. <hi>Burges</hi> Apol. pag. 9. citing <hi>Mooker.</hi>
                  </note> No man can do evil with a good conſcience.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the mind of the Doer certainly apprehend a lawfulneſſe for the doing of it, elſe the conſcience ſinneth through doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119318:30"/>
With this aſſurance of mind and conſcience, who can uſe ſuch Veſtiments as are meerly Eccleſiaſtical, Myſtical Rites, when he cannot find a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> firm Ground out of the Scripture, that God alloweth ſuch under the New Teſtament?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whoſeover doth not admit the Propoſition, he openeth a gap unto Oyl, Cream, Spittle, Candles; holy Water, and other Popiſh Ceremonies to enter into the Church, which our learned Divine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; for this, that they are myſtical ſignificant Rites, deviſed by Man; as is to be ſeen, not by the Judgment of Forraign Divines onely; As of the Church of <hi>Wittenburg. Harm. Confeſſ.</hi> part. 2. artic. 32. <hi>de Corem. Eccleſiaſticis;</hi> The Churches of <hi>France;</hi> and the low Countries in their Obſervations upon the Harmony of Confeſſions. <hi>Ibid.</hi> Sect. 17. <hi>ad Sax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. Confeſſ. Obſerv.</hi> 1. <hi>Calvin in</hi> Eſay 20.2. &amp; Mat. 21.25. Beza <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 8. But alſo our own Divines, Dr. <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift,</hi> Defence of Anſwer to the <hi>Admon. Tract.</hi> 7. cap. 7. diviſ. 8. pag. 291. Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Commentary on <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23, 24, 25. who diſſallow ſuch ſignification of Apparrel in Eccleſiaſtical uſe, as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Hooper</hi> would put upon it. <hi>Loc. commun.</hi> pag. 1088. <hi>Edit.</hi> 1613.</p>
               <p>And further, if the Propoſition be not true,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perkin</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Probl. in Title Apurten. to Maſſe. Sect. 6. Dr. <hi>Morton</hi>'s proteſt. appeal. Lib. 1. Cap. 3. Sect. 5. Pag. 58.</note> Might not a man reaſon thus for the bringing in of Popiſh Rites of the ſame nature and kind? Veſtiments inſtituted by man, and appropriated to God's Worſhip, and of myſtical ſignification, are lawful: Therefore, Oyl, Cream, Spittle, Candles; and other ſuch like Popiſh Rites are lawful alſo.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To conclude, worthy Divines have condemned all Ceremonies when they have been parts of, and appropriated to, Worſhip; As <hi>Calvin. Inſtitut.</hi> Lib. 4. Cap. 10. Sect. 8. Perkins <hi>Reform. Cathel.</hi> p. 136. And doth not Dr. <hi>Abbott</hi> call all Prieſtly Garments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are diſtinguiſhed from the reſt of the Church, a ſpiritual Character of the Beaſt. <hi>Antichr. Demon.</hi> Cap. 11. Sect. 26.</p>
               <p>And whereas for eight hundred years after Chriſt, there were but eight Veſtures uſed in the whole myſteries of Religion, and now among the Papiſts there be fifteen; ſix Prieſtly, and nine of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; What reaſon is there to prove them, or ſuch of them unlawful; which our Law hath rejected, if this Propoſition be not true. The Aſſumption proved.</p>
               <p>In the proof whereof it is requiſite, that I inſiſt upon theſe three Heads.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119318:31"/>
                  <item>1. That the Surplice in our Church is appropriated to God's ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Worſhip, as to meet to Eccleſiaſtial uſe.</item>
                  <item>2. That it is appointed for ſignification of ſpiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Duties.</item>
                  <item>3. That this is done by Man, without Warrant from the Word of God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt of theſe 3 Heads is apparant by the Reaſons following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Albeit young Students in the Univerſities, who by their matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, did receive their <hi>primam tonſuram</hi> into the Clergy:<note place="margin">The Surplice to be appropriated to Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal uſe.</note> Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſters in the Cathedrall Churches being antiently reputed of the Clergy; and ſome Clerks in ſome Parochial and Collegiat Churches, have heretofore, and ſtill do retein the Surplice: Yet we ſee that the uſe is ſtill reſtrained to Worſhip, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Prayers, reading Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, adminiſtration of Sacraments, &amp;c. And out of that uſe it is not to be found, neither is there any civil uſe made of the Surplice. As for buriall of the dead, it is uſed by none but by a Miniſter, or one initiate into the Clergy, and that with ſolemn prayers accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying: Who then can ſay, that the uſe of the Surplice in Burials, is a withdrawing of it from Eccleſiaſtical uſe.</item>
                  <item>2. I might urge what I obſerve out of Dr. <hi>Whitgift,</hi> who denying Pope <hi>Hadrian</hi> to be the Inventer of the Surplice,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Spark</hi>'s perſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. cap. 5. pag. 19.</note> (<hi>Def. Tract.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 1.) would draw the Original thereof from <hi>Stepha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe teſtimony (if it be ought worth) proven that holy Veſtments are not to be touched of any ſave the Prieſt, (<hi>Ibid. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 2.) and conſequently that they are not of civi uſe. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates hominibus. Luc. Oſiand. Epitom. Hiſtor. Eccleſiaſt.</hi> Cent. 3. Lib. 3. Cap. 14.</item>
                  <item>3. In Popery the Surplice was appropriated to God's ſolemn Worſhip, without which no Prieſt might ſay Service. <hi>Miſſal. Rom.</hi> part. 1. <hi>Miſſa in Galli cantu, &amp; Miſſa in die Nativitatis D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Neither could Water or Bells, or any thing elſe be hallowed. <hi>Dr.</hi> Humphry <hi>his Antidiploma miſſal. Rom.</hi> part. 3. pag. 96. And if it were not of the eſſence of the Maſſe, that every Prieſt that ſayth it have a Surplice on, yet ſome Prieſt cannot ſay Maſs without it. <hi>Durand. rational.</hi> Lib. 3. Cap. 1. Numb. 9. Neither can any Prieſt make his breaden-god, except he have it on. <hi>Rh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tat. in</hi> 1 Cor. 11.29.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This I omit to urge, though I muſt confeſs, that hough o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Church hath varied and changed ſomewhat from out immediate fore-fathers the Papiſts, from whom it cometh to us; yet they did
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119318:31"/>not remove it from Eccleſiaſticall Places and Services, or inſtituted a civil or ordinary uſe of the foreſaid Veſtment. Doth not the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the firſt year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> appoint ſuch Ornaments in the Church to be retained (as were in the Church of <hi>England</hi> by Authority of Parliament in the ſecond year of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth,<note place="margin">Cap. 2.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till other Order be taken by the Authority of the Queen, &amp;c.) at the time of the Communion, and other adminiſtration, &amp;c. Was Order taken? No. We muſt judge then, for what kind of uſe the Surplice by the Stature of King <hi>Edward the ſixth</hi> was inſtituted and allowed.</p>
               <p>The words of the Book of Common-Prayer in the ſecond year of his Reign, are theſe; <hi>Upon the Day, and at the time appointed for the Miniſtration of holy Communion; the Prieſt that ſhall execute that holy Ministery, ſhall put on him the Veſtures appointed for that Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</hi> If the uſe of the Surplice ſtand by Statute, it is, for any thing that I know, by this, which declares it to be retained for meer Eccleſiaſtical uſe: If it be ſo, as Dr. <hi>Sparks</hi> ſaith in his Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to uniformity, <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 20. 21. That Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by vertue of the ſaid Statute, by the conſent of the Arch-Biſhop, and High Commiſſioners, in the ſeventh year of her Reign, appointed the Surplice to be worn inſtead of the Albe; yet it hindreth not, but proves what I ſay in this Section.<note place="margin">Can. Eccleſ. 14. &amp; 17.</note> But becauſe this I think is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, I paſs to the ſecond Head in the Aſſumption.</p>
               <p>That the Surplice is ſignificant of ſpiritual Duties, is clear.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All our Eccleſiaſticall Ceremonies are ſuch;<note place="margin">In the Treatiſe of Ceremonies prefixed to that Book.</note> They are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dumb nor dark (ſaith the Book of Common-Prayer) but apt to ſtirr up the dull mind of man to a remembrance of his Duty by ſome notable and ſpecial ſignification.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſaith, Ceremonies deſtitute of ſignification, muſt be vain; alſo he calleth them viſible Signs,<note place="margin">Eccl. Pol. Lib. 5. Sect. 55. Ibid. Lib. 4. Sect. 1.</note> which are undoubtedly moſt effectuall to open ſuch matter, as when men know and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber carefully, they muſt needs be a great deal the better informed: Thus much alſo Dr. <hi>Covell</hi> doth avouch (againſt the Plea of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noc. <hi>pag.</hi> 58.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. To omit that the Papiſts ſay, All their Prieſtly Garments have myſticall ſignification. <hi>Bell. de miſſ.</hi> lib. 6. cap. 14. And that the Prieſt muſt be cloathed in White to ſignifie innocency and purity,<note place="margin">Lindan de C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebr. miſs.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ob reverentiam Salvatoris, &amp; totius Coeleſtis curiae, quam Sacra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>into altar conſiciende, &amp; confecto, non eſt dubium intereſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119318:32"/>
Thoſe Learned men who were ſet awork in the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and ſince (and who therefore were moſt likely to know the meaning of our Church in impoſing) have avouched, That it is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hook.</hi> Eccl. Pol. lib. 5. Sect. 29.</note> and ought to be continued, for ſignification. <hi>Bucer. opera An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glican. pag.</hi> 682. <hi>Pet. Mart. Loc. Comman. pag.</hi> 1088.</p>
               <p>Now concerning the third Head. The Surplice, in that foreſaid uſe and ſignification, is without warrant of the Word of God. It may thus be proved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Surplice being a garment of a ſpecial nature, and uſe, in that it is a meer Eccleſiaſtical and Myſtical Rite, ought to have a ſpecial Divine Inſtitution, as ſuch garments have had in the Church of the Jews: for Reaſon requires that the ground be ſuitable to the nature of the thing. But ſuch a ground it hath not, neither can any ſhew any ſpecial Inſtitution.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is not ſo much as any general warrant for it in the Book of God. Firſt, there is none in the Old Teſtament: The Prieſtly garments were tyed only to the place of Ceremonies,<note place="margin">Exod. 28.43. Ezek. 42.14. <hi>Mornaeus</hi> de Euchariſt.</note> not uſed in any of the Synagogues of the Land, nor in any of thoſe 460 which are reported to be in <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> Were typical, (wherein it ſtands not with the nature of the times of the New Teſtament to mitigate them,<note place="margin">Ezek. 42.13, 14. &amp; 44.15, 17, 19. 1 Chron. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Spark perſwaſ. to uniformity, cap.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 22.) Neither were they uſed in the Peoples ſight, except once extraordinary by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the preſence of the Ark before the People. So that if there had been any further uſe of them <hi>(viz.)</hi> for glory and comelineſs, as one ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spark.</hi> Ibid.</note> not conſidering, that in the uſe alſo they were typicall, yet they cannot poſſibly warrantize Veſtiments in the ſight of the People.</p>
               <p>If the Prophets did uſe ordinarily any apparel whereby they might be known from other men, (which doth ſeem doubtfull to ſome that read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.18. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.41.) yet that which they did wear, was of common and daily uſe, worn in Town and Field, &amp;c. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Eſay</hi> 20.2. <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.14. So that it matters not in this caſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Whitg.</hi> def. tract. 7. cap. 2. pag. 262.</note> though the Prophets were diſcerned by a peculiar form of Cloke, ſeeing it was not of Eccleſiaſtical and Myſtical ſignification, and withall was extraordinary as their Function was. Our Divines condemn the Popiſh Maſſing Garments, becauſe they are Jewiſh. To ſeek ground for the Surplice out of the Levitical Law, is it not then to overthrow our own grounds?</p>
               <p>Further,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.4.</note> in the New Teſtament, there is no ground for the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119318:32"/>The habit of <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was daily and common, not Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical and Myſtical. That Chriſt or his Apoſtles did uſe, or inſtitute any Myſtical or Eccleſiaſtical attire, none can ſhew by the holy Scriptures: and the relation of other Hiſtories is but humane and fallible; not the ground of faith. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. requiring all things to <hi>be done decently and in order in the Aſſemblies of the Saints,</hi> did give commandment for the right and ſeemly performance of ſuch Ordinances as were before eſtabliſhed; but laid no ground for the inſtitution of myſtical Rites in religious ſervices. This ſpeech of the Apoſtle is a Precept, and hath a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine binding power; which not to obey, is death. How can this concern the inſtitution of the Surplice, which is no ſuch matter, but reputed indifferent by the Urgers. What the Apoſtle commands, is neceſſary and indiſpenſable by Man: But the Surplice and other Rites are arbitrary, and may be diſpenſed with, and utterly aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. D. <hi>Morton</hi> in <hi>Proteſt. Appeal lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. <hi>numb.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 54.</p>
               <p>The Surplice is confeſſed to be but an humane tradition:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spark.</hi> Perſwaſ. to Uniform. cap. 5. pag. 21.</note> Who can prove hence, that there is any better ground for the Surplice, than for the 15 Prieſtly Robes uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus doth it appear, that the Scripture affordeth not any warrant for the Surplice in our uſe. I know many Teſtimonies are cited forth of the ancient Writers: but their teſtimony being but humane, proveth not that God doth allow and warrantize the Surplice. Yea, ſome of them do not at all concern Eccleſiaſtical Veſtiments.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 33.</note> Such is that teſtimony, that <hi>Euſtathim</hi> was deprived of his Biſhoprick, for not wearing decent apparel befitting his place.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat.</hi> lib. 6. cap. 20.</note> Such alſo was that white rayment that <hi>Semius</hi> the <hi>Novat.</hi> did wear; and that under-garment of white Linnen, in which <hi>Cyprian</hi> the Martyr ſtood apparelled after he had given his Cap or <hi>Byrrhus,</hi> to the Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and his upper garment called <hi>Dalmatica,</hi> to the Deacon.<note place="margin">Vide Concil. à Binnio Collect. Conc. Gang. cap. 12. part. 385.</note> Such is the garment ſpoken of by the Council of <hi>Gangris,</hi> as he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders it, may ſee.</p>
               <p>So that theſe places are miſ-alledged by D. <hi>Whitgift, Def. tract.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 208. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that likewiſe of <hi>Chryſoſt. Homil.</hi> 6. <hi>ad popul. Antioch.</hi> who ſheweth, That the dignity of the Miniſtery ſtandeth not in going up and down the Church in a white garment, that is, as a gallant white attire being a garment of honour, both in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119318:33"/>the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> parts,<note place="margin">Perk. Probl. t t. The Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu. ten. of the <hi>Maſſe.</hi>
                  </note> and in the Weſt among the ancient <hi>Romans. Sigon. de Jud. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>As for that which the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> is ſaid to went, called a <hi>Miter,</hi> but ratehr a thin plate, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth ſignifie, either <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth thereby (alluding to <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Eccleſ. lib. 3. cap. 25. <hi>Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliam div ſionem</hi> 31. Conference with <hi>Hart,</hi> cap. 8. diviſ. 4. pag. 516.</note> 
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.36.) mean, that <hi>John</hi> entred into the Sanctuary, as it were, with Prerogative, and had the very Myſterie of God revealed to him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1. as Dr. <hi>Rainolds</hi> doth underſtand; or elſe, if this relation deſerve credit, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Euſebius Pamphilus</hi> lived <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 320, about 200 years after the death of him of whom he writeth, and ſaith, <hi>John</hi> was a Biſhop, which agrees not with the Apoſtle's Office and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that was univerſal; yet this habit was a common and daily habit, as the words of the Author rather import.</p>
               <p>Moreover, ſome Teſtimonies urged do concern the Jewiſh Veſtiments, as that of <hi>Jerom</hi> in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. The Religion of God hath one habit, (as Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> confeſſeth. <hi>Eccleſ. Pol. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> 29.)</p>
               <p>Laſtly, though ſome teſtimonies quoted may ſhew, that anciently there were ſome Linnen garments in Eccleſiaſtical uſe, as <hi>Theodoret, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. ſpeaks, of a baptizing robe given by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 1. adverſ. Pelagium.</note> And <hi>Jerome</hi> makes mention of Linnen garments uſed in adminiſtration by Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons. And the Councel of <hi>Carthage,</hi> Can. 41. (where there were 214. Biſhops, of whom <hi>Auſtine</hi> was one) decreed, <hi>Diaconus tempore obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timis tantum, vel lectionis, Albâ induatur.</hi> Yet none of theſe prove, that theſe were inſtituted for myſtical ſignification; or, if they were, that there was warrant from the Word of God for ſo doing.</p>
               <p>Thus the Aſſumption being confirmed, the Concluſion neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily followeth, That the Surplice may not lawfully be uſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>Of the ſign of the Croſſe in Baptiſm.</head>
               <p>THat the uſe of the ſign of the Croſſe in Baptiſm is unlawful, I prove by this Argument:</p>
               <p>No Rite meerly Eccleſiaſtical, and of myſtical ſignification, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119318:33"/>no Warrant from the Word of God, can be uſed without ſin.</p>
               <p>But the ſign of the Croſſe in Baptiſm is a Rite meerly Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, and of myſtical ſignification, having no warrant from Gods Word:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> It cannot be uſed without ſin.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition of this Argument, being in effect the ſame with the Propoſition of the Precedent Argument, (the Croſs and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice being <hi>Homogenea,</hi>) is confirmed by the Reaſons of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Propoſition. I will therefore with great brevity confirm this <hi>Major.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, Such Rites as are meerly Eccleſiaſtical and myſtical, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no warrant from Gods Word, are falſe worſhip: Otherwiſe we ſhall never be able to convince the Papiſts of Will-worſhip in their Superſtitious Rites. Alſo, all actions, whereby religious du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are taught in Gods publick ſervice, are Worſhip: otherwiſe how can the preaching of the Word be worſhip. But Rites, meerly Eccleſiaſtical and myſtical, &amp;c. do teach us ſpiritual and religious duties. Are they not Worſhip then? Yet not true, for they are not divinely warranted. Of neceſſity therefore they muſt be falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Such myſtical Rites are Sacraments not approved of God. Sacraments they be, for they are viſible ſigns of an inviſible grace, and have both the parts of a Sacrament, which are ſet down in the common Catechiſm authoriſed by Law. But theſe are not true Sacraments, when God the Author of the Covenant doth not inſtitute them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Such Rites as are meerly Eccleſiaſtical, and Myſtical, are not diſcernable to be good by the light of Nature; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are to have approbation from Gods Word the rule of Faith: otherwiſe with ſafety of conſcience they cannot be received.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Our Learned Divines ſay, That to bring inſignificant Ceremonies into the Church, is plain Judaiſm. Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with <hi>Hart,</hi> cap. 8. diviſ. 4. pag. 521. <hi>Willet Synopſ.</hi> 2. <hi>gen. Cont.</hi> 24.2. part of the Qu. pag. 110. Edit. 1614.</p>
               <p>The Aſſumption now remains to be proved; and in it three things. 1. That the ſign of the Croſſe is meerly Eccleſiaſticall. 2. Of Myſtical ſignification. 3. Without warrant out of God's Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119318:34"/>
Firſt, There is not the leaſt ſhew, to deny the ſign of the Croſſe to be meerly Eccleſiaſtical: For other uſe of the ſign of the Croſſe, than in Baptiſm, we deny. Indeed, anciently it was ordinary in common uſe, as well as in Eccleſiaſtical. So likewiſe it is with the Papiſts: but ordinary Croſſing, morning and evening, is condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our Divines: and the Law requireth, urgeth, and alloweth only the uſe of the Croſſe in Baptiſm: wherein if it be not of meer Eccleſiaſtical uſe, what can Ecclefiaſticall uſe be defined to be?</p>
               <p>Secondly, Can there be produced any likelihood, or ſhew of truth, to deny the ſign of the Croſſe to be of myſtical ſignification, ſeeing all our Ceremonies are ſuch, as was before ſhewed: and the words of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> do teach as much, ſaying, <hi>We receive this Child into the Congregation, &amp;c. and do ſign him with the ſign of the Croſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Can. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>in token that hereafter, &amp;c.</hi> And the Canon ſaith, <hi>That the Child baptized, is dedicated to God by the ſign of the Croſſe.</hi> Theſe things, I ſuppoſe, do prove the ſign of the Croſs to be of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical ſignification.</p>
               <p>Now it remains, that I ſhew, That this myſtical Rite is without warrant out of the Word of God. This may be proved by theſe Arguments following.</p>
               <p>Though the Croſſe, being a Rite of a peculiar nature, ought to ſhew for it ſelf a peculiar and ſpecial Inſtitution; yet it is ſo void of that, that there is not ſo much as a general warrant for it in the Book of God. As the examination of the places cited by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, or Proteſtants, will manifeſt.</p>
               <p>I omit to mention in this ſhort abridgment,<note place="margin">Juſt. Martyr <hi>in</hi> Tryphone.</note> ſome Inſtances for the Croſſe, though uſed by the Ancients, which have not ſo much as a colour of the truth, and will produce theſe few Inſtances.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) The mark which was ſet in the forehead of the mourners, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.9. is urged to prove the ſign of the Croſs lawful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. <hi>Tau,</hi> tranſlated a mark, doth ſignifie in common any ſign, as <hi>Arius Montanus,</hi> and <hi>Paguin,</hi> in their Dictionaries, ſhew. The Vulgar Greek, called the 70, tranſlate it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The form of <hi>Tau</hi> being this η, makes nothing for the Croſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This was an inviſible mark, and peculiar to the Elect; ſuch as that was, <hi>Apoo.</hi> 7.3. &amp; 9.4.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Proteſtarts Object the Altar built on <hi>Jordan's</hi> bank; the Altar built by <hi>Solomon;</hi> the Muſick uſed in the Temple; the Love-Feaſts
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119318:34"/>which were in uſe in the Primitive Church; and the Kiſſe of love, as grounds to warrant our uſe of the ſign of the Croſs. To all which Inſtances, I anſwer in order.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The Altar that ſtood on <hi>Jordan's</hi> Bank, was not of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, but of Civil uſe.<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bington</hi> on the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</note> The Tribes confeſs that they had indeed grievouſly ſinned, if they had determined an Altar to the ſame uſe, for which the Lord had ſet up one before. It was a memorial, that they were one people with their brethren, entitled to, and eſtated in the Priviledges of the Lord with them: but it was no myſticall ſign of Chriſt and his grace.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ma. Sutclif.</hi> contr <hi>Bellar.</hi> de Sum. Pont. lib. 1. cip. 6. <hi>Franc. Jun.</hi> Contr. 3. lib. 4. cap. 17. nota. 4.</note> If <hi>Solomon</hi> built not his new Altar by extraordinary Inſpiration as a Prophet (as one ſaith): Yet he did it out of the equity of <hi>Moſes,</hi> s Law it ſelf, and was no addition at all of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe kind. And it it moſt certain, That God who by his viſible deſcending, did approve of the whole work of the Temple when it was done, did authorize him for the doing of it; which <hi>David</hi>'s words may alſo confirm, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.19.</p>
               <p>The Muſick uſed in the Temple, was ſpecially appointed of God, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.4. &amp; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.5. and both the Altar and it were Typical, tyed to the place of Ceremonies, and continuing but with them.</p>
               <p>As concerning the Love-Feaſts, if they were of Apoſtolick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, (ordained by the Apoſtles, as they were immediately gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by that Spirit which infallibly did aſſiſt them in their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Function) they were Divine, (for it is not Apoſtolick in that ſenſe, and divine the ſame? Dr. <hi>Abb. anſwer to W. Biſh. cap. 7. of Tradir. Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>Fran. Junius animadv. in Bellar. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>not.</hi> 6.) and had a ſpecial appointment from God; which the Croſſe hath not. But if none knoweth by whom they were brought in, yet they are abrogated there by the Apoſtle; where we find firſt mention of them: neither were they of myſtical ſanctification, and are not yet proved to be of meer Eccleſiaſtical uſe.</p>
               <p>To conclude, <hi>Oſculum pacis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſt. Marti</hi> Apoc. 2. <hi>ad finem. Durant.</hi> de rit. lib. 2. cap. 54. Sect. 7.</note> which went before the Solemnity of the Supper, to prepare men to the worthy receiving in Charity, was in tract of time diſliked, and degenerated into the kiſſing of the <hi>Pax.</hi> This I ſay was a natural indicant Sign of Peace and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, as embracing, ſhaking hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and other the like acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:119318:35"/>
If the Sign of the Croſs be in ſome ancient Writers called Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick, they are to be underſtood in no other ſenſe than as they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lent-Faſts, the Creed, Saturdaies, and Wedneſdaies, Faſts-Apoſtolick. <hi>Et praecepta Majorum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Jerom</hi>) <hi>unaquae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> provincia leges Apoſtolicas arbitratur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerom.</hi> Epiſt. ad <hi>Luc.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, whereas it may ſeem that <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Viſion was a divine ratification of the uſe of the Croſs; I anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Narration is humane and fallible.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The words of the Hiſtorian be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>de vitâ</hi> Conſtan. l. 1. c. 22. <hi>Soc.</hi> lib. 1. c. 1.</note> which do rather import, In this Chriſt, than in this Sign.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſight which appeared was, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>made after the faſhion of a Croſs,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>A maerk of Chriſt's Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The mark containeth the two firſt Letters of Chriſt's Name, ΧΡ, So that Ρ was made, and Χ by croſſing (as it were) a Spear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlope, after this manner ΧΡ. Nothing hitherto hath proved the Sign of the Croſs to be warranted by the Word of God; and that which follows will prove that it is meerly humane, if not worſe.</p>
               <p>Was not the Heretick <hi>Valentinus</hi> the begetter of this Sign, who gave it the ſame effective Power that the Papiſts do,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi> Arg. in <hi>Rhem.</hi> Teſt. Luc. 22.5. <hi>ex Iraen.</hi> l. 1. c. 1. <hi>Magdeburg.</hi> Cen. 3. cap. 10.</note> as our learned Writer ſaith? Was not <hi>Montanus</hi> the firſt that gave it credit? Was not <hi>Tertullian</hi> the chief Inſtrument under him, that ſo much commendeth it, (a man well known to be infamous after his Fall)? <hi>Deering</hi> on the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Lect. 2. And did not the Superſtition of the People further the breeding of it up: D. <hi>Royn,</hi> Confer. with <hi>Hart.</hi> cap. 8. diviſ. 4. pag. 504.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambr.</hi> in Epiſt. ad <hi>Rom.</hi> cap. 8.</note> So did it appear, when it was ſaid, <hi>Signatos Cruce in morte ſecunda Diabolus tenere non audet: Care ſignatur, ut Anima muniatur.</hi> Tettul. <hi>de Reſurrect. carnis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this be the original of the Sign of the Croſs, the creeping of it into Baptiſm cannot be by divine appointment.</p>
               <p>But to conclude, if this Sign be indifferent (as it is acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the maintainers of it,) then the inſtituting of the uſe of it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be more than humane. Out of theſe premiſes it is eaſy to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the unlawfulneſs of the Croſs in Baptiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119318:35"/>
               <head>Of Kneeling in the Act of receiving the Sacramental Bread and Wine.</head>
               <p>I Acknowledge that the Supper of the Lord ought to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with all due Reverence, yet ſo that the rule and meaſure of that reverence be the Word of God, not the Will and Wit of Man: To which rule, becauſe I know not how this kneeling doth agree, therefore I dare not ſubmit to the practice of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Argumen."/> My Argument againſt it I thus diſpoſe.</p>
               <p>No bodily religious Adoration of God, before any Creature, with reſpect unto it, having no allowance from God, can be lawfully uſed:</p>
               <p>But kneeling in the Act of receiving the Sacramental Bread and Wine, is a bodily religious Adoration of God before a Creature, with reſpect unto it, having no ſpecial allowance from God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> It cannot be lawfully uſed.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition may be juſtified by four reaſons.<note place="margin">Propoſition.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scriptures are ſo perfect in matters of Worſhip, that they ſhut out all humane Inventions: Therein God blaming what is not according to his Commandment, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.31. and 195. his revealed Will being the All-ſufficient Rule of Worſhip, <hi>Dout.</hi> 12.31, 32. which both ancient Writers (Chryſoſt. <hi>in Epist.</hi> 2. <hi>ad</hi> Corinth. <hi>Homil.</hi> 13. <hi>Baſil</hi> Epiſt. 80.) and modern alſo do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch, while they maintain the Scriptures to be the total Rule of Faith and Manners: <hi>Proteſtant's Appeal.</hi> l. 2. c. 25. Sect. 11. <hi>Theſ. Joh Reynolds</hi> Theſ. 1. Sect. 3. <hi>White</hi>'s <hi>Way,</hi> Sect. 5. Digreſ. 3. And many other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such Worſhip the Propoſition diſalloweth,<note place="margin">Hook. <hi>Eccleſ. Pol.</hi> l. 5. Sect. 3.</note> as Will-worſhip or Superſtition; which is a Religion forged by Man, the root where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Ignorance of mind, miſ-guided zeal, and falſe fear. This is and hath been condemned and puniſhed by the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.12. &amp; 29.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3. <hi>Numb.</hi> 3.4. and judged flat Idolatry both by ancient and modern Writers,<note place="margin">Aug <hi>de Conſen Evan.</hi> l. 1. c. 18.</note> both Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119318:36"/>and Popiſh. Dr. <hi>Bilſon. Apol.</hi> part. 4. pag. 344. <hi>Vaſq. de Adorat.</hi> lib. 2, Diſput. 1. cap. 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſecond Commandment doth condemn relative Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God without ſpecial Warrant: For it requireth that we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the true God purely, according to his Will. For the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding of it, obſerve two things to be forbidden in this Commandment.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The making of an Image for religious uſe, and under this by a Trope (wherein a part is put for the whole) all Forms of Worſhip deviſed by Man, are forbidden.</item>
                  <item>2. The adoring of an Image, or Form of Worſhip of his own head: So that if a man make an Image for ſacred uſe, though he do not actually adore it, yet is he a Tranſgreſſor of this Law. If of his own head he bow down to any form of Worſhip, though he did not deviſe it, yet is he an Offender.</item>
               </list>
               <p>If any ſhould ſay, That the Lord hath forbidden making of an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or Form of Worſhip, and the worſhipping and ſerving of that onely which he deviſed, but not the adoring of God's own Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; he doth ſo ſtreighten the ſenſe of the Law, that Popiſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of the Sacrament would eſcape the cenſure of this Law,<note place="margin">Proteſ. Appeal. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 29. S. 3. <hi>White</hi>'s Way pag. 519.</note> and ſo ſhould be unjuſtly blamed in the Papiſts: Alſo he openeth a gap to the Jews to have worſhipped Manna, and all the Sacrifices of the Law; and to Chriſtians, with religious Worſhip bodily to adore the Bible, Baptiſm, yea, the Miniſter himſelf, without Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of this Commandment: It cannot then be denyed, but that relative Adoration of God before his Ordinances, with reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to them without ſpecial licence, is here forbidden. Learned Divines have laid this down as an Axiom in Divinity,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> of Stage-Playes.</note> That a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive precept ſtandeth in all the parts of it in force, except the Lord of the Law lay down ſo plain a diſpenſation of the Law, or any branch of it, that a Man's Conſcience upon good grounds may reſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that God doth exempt him from the Power of his Law, in this or that particular caſe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal. 99.5.</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lv Piſcat. Vatabl. Muſcul. in loc.</note> as the Jews were diſpenſed with by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Appointment, requiring they ſhould worſhip their God before the Ark and Temple, in ſuch a ſenſe as they did not before their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and other legal Rites. <hi>Fulk</hi> againſt <hi>Rhem.</hi> in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>De lib.</hi> Concord. Admon. Chriſt. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Perkins</hi> Treatiſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and relig. Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:119318:36"/>
4, The Brazen Serpent, ſet up by the appointment of God,<note place="margin">Numb. 21.8. Joh. 3.15. Exod. 32.4. Judg. 3.13. 2 King. 10.26, 27. Dr. <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nolds</hi> lib. 2. <hi>de Idol.</hi> cap. 2. S. 5.</note> was a lively Type of Chriſt, was reſerved as a memorial of ſpecial di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mercy, and in proceſs of time the Jews did worſhip God reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectively before it, not determining their Worſhip in it; as may be gathered from Examples in Scripture compared, and from the Judgment of the learned: yet becauſe they offered Incenſe before it to God, without ſpecial Warrant, their Fact was condemned, and the brazen Serpent demoliſhed.</p>
               <p>The Propoſition being confirmed,<note place="margin">Aſſumpt.</note> the Aſſumption is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. In the proof whereof four things are to be inſiſted upon.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That kneeling in the Act of Receiving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a Worſhip.</item>
                  <item>2. No civil but a religious Worſhip.</item>
                  <item>3. That it is a relative Adoration of God, before a Creature with reſpect unto it.</item>
                  <item>4. There is no ſpeciall Warrant, nor Appointment from God for it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Concerning the firſt branch, That kneeling is a Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a geſture of the body, uſed to teſtify, ſignify, and ſhadow out the inward and hidden Act of the mind to ſome perſon or thing.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perkins</hi> Caſe of Conſc. l. 2. cap. 11. Sect. 1.</note> This the learned acknowledge to be Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If a man ſhould bow in ſuch ſort, as he doth in the Sacrament unto God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.6. to his Prince, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1.23, 31. to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.12. to the Chair of State; to an Angel, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.2. &amp; 19.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10. to his Superiour, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.3, 6. &amp; 42.6, 9. compared with 37.7, 9. yea, to an Idol, is he not ſaid to give Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to that whereto he kneeleth?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Reverend kneeling and bowing of the body is expreſſed by ſuch words in the Scripture, that ſignify outward Worſhip,<note place="margin">Scultetus <hi>de Precatione</hi> par. 2. &amp; Concor. Graec. <hi>de voce</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.2. &amp; 23.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.8, 11.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Evangeliſt <hi>Mark</hi> recording the Story of the Leper that came to Chriſt, ſaith, that he kneeled down, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.40. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith that <hi>he fell on his face,</hi> Chap. 5.12. and <hi>Matthew,</hi> that he worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.2.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Kneeling in the act of receiving is not intended by ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or obeyers, for eaſe, or civil furtherance. It's no geſture of neceſſity, as it is in them, who being lame, kneel,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 9.22.</note> becauſe they can do no otherwiſe. Neither is it a geſture of order to kneel at a Feaſt, whether Spiritual, or Corporal; and what order can there be when moſt do ſit or ſtand to attend the Word read, to ſing Pſalms, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119318:37"/>&amp;c. that the perſon communicating ſhould kneel. But if that be true which ſome have ſaid,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that the Greek words uſed by the Evangeliſt, ſpeaking of the geſture uſed by the Lord Jeſus in his Paſſover, and conſequently alſo in his Supper, do rather ſignify kneeling than ſitting; a man might have ſome colour to avouch, that nature, reaſon, and cuſtome, taught rather to kneel at ſome Feaſts, than to ſit or ſtand.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> But the truth is, that the Evangeliſt uſe two words to expreſs the geſture of our Saviour. The one is ordinarily rendred, ſitting, as may be ſeen in theſe places, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.10. and 26.7.20. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.18. and 16.14. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.37. and 22.27. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.11. or gueſts, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.10, 11. or ſuch as are at a Table, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.28. and ſcarce more than once it's tranſlated lying down, <hi>Mark</hi> 5.40. and once leaning, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.28. The former of theſe not concerning any geſture, and the latter ſhewing their nationall manner and faſhion of ſitting.</p>
               <p>The other word is tranſlated,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſitting, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.35. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.40. and 8.6. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.37. and 14.10. and 17.7. and 22.14. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.10. and 13.12. and, it may be, not above once otherwiſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.20. Theſe words are tranſlated ſitting by our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlators,<note place="margin">Joh. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yn. plect. 79. pag. 941, 942. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. Bez. in Joh. 13.23.</note> as in the late Tranſlation in the <hi>Geneva,</hi> and in that of the great Bibles to which we were tyed by Law to ſubſcribe. <hi>Beza, Piſcator, Arias Montanus,</hi> the vulgar Interpreter, the Doctors of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> do thus tranſlate them: and do not Grecians know, that theſe words do properly note the geſture of ſitting? Indeed the faſhion of ſitting in the Oriental parts,<note place="margin">Perk. Caſe of Conſc. l. 2. c. 11. S. 1. And Com. in Matth. 4.9.</note> was different from that that is uſed in the Northern Climates; but National circumſtances carry not the nature of geſture. I conclude then, that ſeeing this knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is not a geſture of neceſſity, eaſe, order, or civill furtherance; it is a geſture of reverence and worſhip.</p>
               <p>Secondly, kneeling in the act, &amp;c. is a Religious worſhip; for all bodily worſhip is Civil, or Religious. Civill is ſuch as is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Inhabitants of the ſame ſociety, as of man to man in reſpect of ſuperiority in office,<note place="margin">Perk. Caſe, l. 2. c. 11. Sect. 1.</note> age, or gifts. This is performed by man, but to ſuch with whom he doth converſe, and then onely to Angells when they had viſible communion with man. Such civill adoration, kneeling in the act of receiving, is not: for what finite ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial object is there preſent at the Communion, to which kneeling ſhould be performed? To worſhip man at that time with ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn worſhip, is to worſhip God by the halves, if not to give that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119318:37"/>to man which God doth appropriate to himſelf. Humane Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty commanding this geſture, doth not make it civil, no more then it makes Prayers, &amp;c. civill actions, by enjoyning them to be made. Seeing this is not a civill geſture, it muſt needs be Religious.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Religious adoration, as it is an oppoſite member to civil, is Spiritual and unlimitted in all places, at all times, and in all thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cauſing him that worſhippeth to adore before that which is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and this is performed to God, or ſomething that is reputed and worſhipped as God. Of this kind is the kneeling in queſtion, as the chief Patrons of conformity do aver, ſaying,<note place="margin">Whitg. def. p. 598. tract. 15. c. 1. Div. 2.</note> that it is the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and fitteſt in reſpect of Prayer and Thankſgiving.</p>
               <p>It is a geſture of Piety, and more neceſſary in this act than in any other. <hi>Hook. Eccleſ. Pol. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>S.</hi> 68. <hi>Cov.</hi> againſt <hi>Burg.</hi> p. 143. Of this kneeling, the Book of Common Prayer Authorized by King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, ſaith, it is commanded <hi>for ſignification of the humble and gratefull acknowledgment of the benefits of Chriſt given to the worthy receiver.</hi> Add further, that ſuch kneeling as this, done to Idolls, would be an Idolatrous worſhip; which could not be, except it were a Religious worſhip.</p>
               <p>To conclude, bowing the knee doth ſometimes in the Scripture note the whole worſhip of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.6. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.18. <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.2. From all this, the concluſion may be inferred, that kneeling in the act of receiving is a Religious worſhip.</p>
               <p>This kneeling is a relative adoration of God before a Creature, with reſpect unto it. The Sacrament is a conſecrated Creature, and before the Sacramental Bread and Wine, we are required to bow. In the intention of the Law, and in the opinion of the moſt people, there is a relation had in the very act of bowing unto the Sacrament, though it be not the object in which they purpoſe their adoration ſhould determine. Is there not the like reſpect as the Papiſts have, when they kneel, or knock their breaſts before a Croſs, or Crucifix, &amp;c?</p>
               <p>The act of kneeling, and the Circumſtances thereof, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, that there is ſuch a relation: for we are allowed to ſit, or ſtand meditating, or ſinging Pſalms, &amp;c. untill we be about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacramental Bread and Wine, and when it is given by the Miniſter to be received by us; Law requires that we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently fall down on our knees, and the practice of moſt is ſutable
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119318:38"/>ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to. Searce is there (if any) more viſible ſign and token to the eye of the ſpectator, to convince the Papiſts of adoration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, than this our bowing at this time is to declare that there is an actual reverence had to the Sacrament when we kneel to God before it. If a man were not onely to bow before it, but to it, what could he do more? If, in this ſenſe, and after this manner, a man ſhould bow to an Image; would not wiſe men judg this act an adoring of the Image, or of God before it? The Book of Common Prayer of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, enjoyneth this poſture to avoid the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>The urgers and maintainers of kneeling,<note place="margin">Th. Hutton. part. 2. p. 54.56. Eccl. regim. p. 140. Spar. perſwaſ. to unifor. c. 4. Th. Hurt. part. 2. pag. 62.</note> tell us in plain tearms, That kneeling is done to the Bread and Wine, not ſimply, but as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Chriſt; that none is ſo ſottiſh to adore the ſign, but the thing repreſented by that ſign; that our bowing is an outward reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence meet to be performed, becauſe of the holy action in hand; that its done to keep the Sacrament in reverence, &amp;c. and that we kneel to put difference between ordinary Bread and Wine, and theſe Sacramental, to which we give more reverence, becauſe its more then ordinary Bread and Wine; and partly to ſtir up in our ſelves and others a more Religious eſtimation of theſe Divine Seals, partly to remove all profane thoughts of contemners and deſpiſers of the Sacrament of the body and bloud of our Lord Jeſus; partly to put a difference hereby from our common bread and Wine which we take in our houſes, and at our Tables; and partly to teach us to lift up our hearts to God to bleſs his own Ordinance. In a word, Articles have been put into, and allowed in Eccleſiaſticall Courts, which have charged the Miniſters to have delivered the Sacrament unreverently to the people, not kneeling. To omit the opinion of the vulgar, who come, as they ſay themſelves, to receive their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; or who place holineſs in the outward bowing, and have relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Sacramentall Signs, which yet addeth ſome ſtrength to the matter in hand.<note place="margin">Eccl. Pol. l. 5. Sect. 5.</note> I conclude with Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> who ſaith well, In actions of this kind, we are more to reſpect what the greateſt part of men is prone to conceive, then what ſome few mens wits may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe in conſtruction of their own particular meaning.</p>
               <p>Now it remains that I aſſay to prove, that kneeling in the act of receiving, hath no ſpecial warrant from the Word. This geſture being proved to be a relative adoration of God before a conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Creature, it is of a ſpecial and peculiar nature and uſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119318:38"/>ought to have a peculiar warrant from God to authorize it, otherwiſe geſtures of this kind cannot be uſed in Faith; for theſe are not diſcernable by the light of Nature; neither can the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rules of the Scripture yield ground for ſuch. When the act done is of ſpecial nature, it muſt have a peculiar direction. The <hi>Jews</hi> did not worſhip towards the High Prieſt, or his Attire,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.11. Exod. 15.16. Exod. 12.11. 1 Cor. 5.7. and 10.3, 4.</note> towards the Paſchal Lamb, the Manna, the water of the Rock, or their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, in that ſenſe as they did before the Ark of the Covenant, or the Mercy-ſeat in the Tabernacle, or in the Temple, although theſe holy things were Types of Chriſt. Nature could not teach, neither yet any general rules in the Scripture why, before one rather than before another, they ſhould bow; therefore for this peculiar adoration, there was a ſpecial appointment.<note place="margin">Numb. 21.8.</note> When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> alſo were ſtinged with fiery Serpents, they looked up at the Brazen Serpent which was a Type of Chriſt, that they might be healed, but this was by ſpecial direction.</p>
               <p>Now as for kneeling in the act of receiving, who can ſhew any peculiar inſtitution. Moreover, Canonical kneeling is not authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Gods Word, nor by any general rule.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Both maintainers and urgers of this geſture, ſay, it is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; and that it was ſo reputed by the State, appears by this, that in the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, ſtanding was ordained at <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Northampton,</hi> by vertue of her Highneſs Commiſſion, and kneeling aboliſhed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt and his Apoſtles at the firſt inſtitution of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, did not kneel; which they would have done,<note place="margin">Matth. 26.20, 26. Mar. 14.18.22. Luk. 22.14.17. Joh. 13.12.</note> if this geſture had been divinely ratified.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Apoſtles after Chriſt's Reſurrection delivered nothing concerning the Lords Supper, but what they received of the Lord. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. and yet delivered the whole counſell of God, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.20.27. but yet ſay nothing of kneeling; which doubtleſs they would have done if it had been a divine Ordinance. Knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is not of that antiquity to have ground or inſtitution by the Apoſtles. That mention which may ſeem to be of it in <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Homil. 5. in diverſ. Evang. loca.</note> is nothing, the book being counterfeit. <hi>Rob. Cocus in Cenſuram quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundam veterum Script. pag.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> her bowing before the Communion Table, or Altar, was in the night intended for Prayer,<note place="margin">Sozem. lib. 8. cap. 5.</note> not to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119318:39"/>
About the year of our Lord 157,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Hiſt. Eccleſ. lib. 7. cap. 8, or 9. <hi>Bez.</hi> Tractar. the large Vol. 3. Part. 183. <hi>De Coron.</hi> milit. cap. 3. Can. 20. <hi>De Spir.</hi> Sanct. cap. 27. <hi>Gentillettus</hi> exam. concil. Triden. lib. 2. Sect. 4. pag. 44. Dr <hi>Fulk.</hi> anſw. to <hi>Rhem.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.29. Sect. 2.4 <hi>Jewel</hi>'s reſp. artic. 8. diviſ. 1. Zach. <hi>Urſ.</hi> common. Chitr. conſid. error. 3. conſid. Bale in the Life of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius</hi> 3. Tho. Mort. Pret. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal. lib. 4. cap. 29. Sect. 3. <hi>Hiſpin.</hi> Hiſt. Sacra. part. 1. lib. 4. <hi>Francis While</hi>'s anſw. to the Treatiſe called, <hi>White dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed black</hi> part. 2. p. 347. <hi>Perk.</hi> Idol. of laſt times, laſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, &amp;c. <hi>Willet</hi> Synopſ. contr. 13. q. 4. pag. 649. edit. 1614. <hi>John White</hi>'s way to the true Church Sect. 50. Num. 9. Stat. 1. Eliz. cap. 2.</note> it may appear that Standing was uſed at the Communion.</p>
               <p>About the year 160, <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> giveth not the leaſt inkling of this Geſture, but mentioneth the Peoples coming to the Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> (who was about 180 or 200 years after Chriſt) reports, That in his time they uſed not to kneel at prayer upon any Lords Day, or upon any other Day between <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> 327, a ſolemn Decree was made, That none might pray kneeling, but ſtanding, upon the Lords Day: This continued in <hi>Baſil's</hi> time, (if that Book was his) <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 380, and was afterward confirmed by the ſixth Council holden at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> So that either the antient Churches never received the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament on the Lords Day (which is without controverſy moſt falſe), or they uſed a Geſture of greater reverence in receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Bread and Wine than they did at prayer, (whereof there is no likelihood); or elſe it muſt be granted, That they were accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to receive the Communion with ſome other Geſture than kneeling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 380, in <hi>Gregory Nazianzen's</hi> time, the People ſtood at the Communion about the Table. I will for brevity omit other perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Teſtimonies for this purpoſe which he that will may read in the Acts and Monuments in the difference between the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that now is and the antient. The ſum of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Gentiles, &amp;c. Alſo in the Dialogue between Cuſtom and Truth, pag. 1264. <hi>Edit.</hi> 1610.</p>
               <p>To draw to an end, very many of our learned Worthies do affirm, That odoration, or bowing before the Sacrament came into uſe, in the dayes of <hi>Honorius</hi> the third. But whatſoever the Original of it was, That which I have ſpoken ſheweth that it is but a humane Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Seeing therefore that kneeling in the Act of receiving the Sacramentall Bread and Wine, is a religious adoration of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a conſecrated Creature with reſpect unto it, having no ſpeciall Warrant out of the Word of God, it cannot be uſed without ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hitherto of the Arguments directly concluding the unlawfulneſs of the controverted Rites.</hi> Now follow the conſiderations for which our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt not to be urged unto conformity, may ſeem reaſonable.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was not the intent of the Statute by which the Ceremonies ſtand in force to perpetuate the uſe of them, but onely to tolerate them out of hope of a fitter time of reformation. This Law was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119318:39"/>to be reverſed, or the benefit thereof to denyed,<note place="margin">In the Procla. prefixed, and ſet before the Book of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.</note> though the Proclamation of his Highneſs did ratify the Authority of the Biſhops to make Eccleſiaſtical Canons, as the words of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation do import; — moſt humbly deſiring us to give our royal aſſent unto the ſaid Canons.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Non-conformity proceeding from fear of ſinning againſt God,<note place="margin">Treatiſe of Ceremonies prefixed before the Book of Common-prayer. And Stat. 1. Eliz. cap. 2. B. <hi>Bilſon.</hi> ag a. Apol. part. 2. pag. 349. <hi>Mort.</hi> anſw. to the Popiſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. 30.</note> is neither contempt, nor ſcandall; and therefore may be allowed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the eye of the Law. If a bare omiſſion of a Rite were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, then all that uſe Bowling which the Law diſſalloweth, and do not were Caps and ſuch Habits as the Statute enjoyneth, ſhall be Contemners. Where we dare not do, we are ready without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting to ſuffer; and ſuffering is as ſure a Sign of ſubjection, as obeying. In ſome caſes, the Law is ſatisfied by ſubmitting a mans ſelf to the Mulct. Neither is forbearance a ſcandall, becauſe it afford, no hurtfull concluſion, which may be naturally and neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thence deduced; except as much and more, may be deduced from ſome Conformities, that do not uſe the Ceremonies ſo oft as the Law requireth. The rayling Inferences of ſome malicious Papiſts, are but meer inconſequences; and do not proceed from our forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but from their malice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The uſe of Ceremonies ought to be free. This the Law ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth probably to import,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jewel</hi> of the private Maſs tract. 2. div. 9. in the end of his anſw. Stat. 13. Eliz. cap. 12</note> which enjoyneth ſubſcription with this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to the Articles of Religion, which onely concern the confeſſion of the true Chriſtian Faith, and the Doctrine of the Sacraments. This practice (onely) limits ſubſcription to the things expreſſed, leaving as it may ſeem other things at liberty. Neither was there any hurt that came to the Church of God by the free uſe of the Ceremonies in the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign.<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> his ſpeech at <hi>Garnet's</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment. P. <hi>Mart.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>cuidam in Angl. Scripta an.</hi> 1559 <hi>Vide</hi> loc com. p. 1225. <hi>Bucer. cenſura.</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſaubon</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi> Eccleſ. Pol. 1. Lib. 5. Sect. 67.</note> For the ſpace of 10 years Papiſts came generally to the Church, but ſince the urging of theſe Rites, they have not been ſo forward. This God hath not bleſſed the impoſing of them, as the leaving of them free.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Worthy men, the maintainers of theſe Rites in the Dayes of King <hi>Edward;</hi> (viz.) <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Bullinger,</hi> upon better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideration, did retract their Judgments.</p>
               <p>Forraign Divines diſallow theſe Rites, and may not we be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to doubt of them?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Since the urging of theſe Ceremonies, theſe Points have ſprung up for the defence of them; <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Churche's Authority binds
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119318:40"/>the Conſcience, That it's not to be enquired into, whether Chriſt be preſent in the Sacrament by Conſubſtantiation or Tranſubſtantiation, and that it doth no way hinder or further us, however it ſtandeth. That relative adoration of God before a Creature with reſpect unto it, without ſpeciall Warrant, may be lawful, &amp;c. May not this breed ſome doubt of the quality of the cauſe, that is by great Schollars thus maintained?</p>
               <p n="6">6. As yet we have nothing to ſettle our doubting-conſciences upon, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe two Points, which yet are not without ſome doubt.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the Rites impoſed are indifferent.</item>
                  <item>2. That in ſuch things, the Churche's or Magiſtrate's Authority binds the Conſcience.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Yet are we taught that no individual Action is indifferent, (<hi>Thom. Mort. Apolog.</hi> Lib. 1. Cap. 47.) indifferency reſting in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Nature, (<hi>Aquin.</hi> 1.2, 18. <hi>Artic.</hi> 97. That, <hi>particulares Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratuum leges mullum habent in conſcientias dominatum.</hi> Whitak. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Duraeum.</hi> Lib. 8. Sect. <hi>ultim.</hi> That no man incurreth the guilt of Damnation, but by breaking the Laws of God. Dr. <hi>Pield</hi> of the Church, <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 33. to which purpoſe ſome other Worthies do write: <hi>Perkin</hi>'s Treatiſe of Conſcience, <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. in the end. If it ſhould be ſaid that the uſe of the Vail, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. may afford Warrant unto us, for ſuch Rites as are in Queſtion. We are to conſider, That the uſe of the Vail was in ordinary uſe, not in meer Eccleſiaſtical uſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.65. Alſo it was not not a Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Sign, but a Natural indicant Sign of modeſty. This conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, doth not our humble ſuit ſeem reaſonable, that till theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions be better cleared, we may be foreborn?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Reſolution in matter of Ceremonies is not eaſy, becauſe the holy Scriptures which in weightier matters is clear, is more dark in things of leſſer moment. So that the <hi>Media</hi> to be uſed in Argument either for,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin.</hi> inſtit. Lib. 4. Cap. 10. Sect. 8. <hi>Beza</hi> Epiſt. 24. Zanch. de ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib. Redemp. cap. 4. <hi>de cultu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tern. qu.</hi> 4. Dr. <hi>White</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. p. 287.</note> or againſt, the Ceremonies are difficult to be found out: Hence it is, That from the beginning there have been great Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, and that among the greateſt, in matter of Ceremonies; as <hi>Bellarm.</hi> ſaith, <hi>De effect. Sacram.</hi> Lib. 2. Cap. 3.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Are learned Proteſtants deceived or not, when they ſay, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Ceremonies are to be condemned, becauſe there is an opinion of holineſs, neceſſity, and worſhip annexed, wherewith they are urged? Or can our's be freed from this holineſs or neceſſity, ſeeing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119318:40"/>they are reputed religious Rites, and urged under a great penalty, both upon Miniſter and People, as the Canons ſhew.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Laſtly, If this Propoſition be true that is given and agreed of by the Learned; Rites of meer humane Invention, of no neceſſary uſe, antiently abuſed to Idolatry, now ſuperſtitiouſly uſed among many ignorant perſons, are to be aboliſhed: It is a worthy labour to reſolve us that our Ceremonies be not ſuch. We are taught,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> Synopſ. 2. Gen. Contr. qu. 3. part. 2. p. 110. Edit. 1614. <hi>Tho: Rogers</hi> his expoſ. of the 39. artic. Act. 20. pag. 101. 102.</note> that Ceremonies to be in the Church, muſt not be in nature impious, in uſe ſuperſtitions; for their weight not over heavy, and grievous to be born; that for their worthineſs in the eyes of the Ordainers, they be neither of an equall prize, nor of more account then the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, ſo as, for the performance of them, the Law of God muſt be left undone; that they be not againſt the liberty of Chriſtians, or any way contrary to the Commandment of God: but tend both to the nouriſhing and increaſe of Love, friendſhip and quietneſs among Chriſtians, and retaining of God's People in God's holy fear, &amp;c.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
